^ (Prov. 1:1-6:35) The proverbs of Solʹo·mon, the son of David, the king of Israel:  2 To learn* wisdom and discipline; To understand wise sayings;  3 To acquire the discipline that gives insight, Righteousness, good judgment,* and uprightness;*  4 To impart shrewdness to the inexperienced; To give a young man knowledge and thinking ability.  5 A wise person listens and takes in more instruction; A man of understanding acquires skillful direction*  6 To understand a proverb and a puzzling saying,* The words of the wise and their riddles.  7 The fear of* Jehovah is the beginning of knowledge. Only fools despise wisdom and discipline.  8 Listen, my son, to the discipline of your father, And do not forsake the instruction* of your mother.  9 They are an attractive wreath for your head And a fine ornament for your neck. 10 My son, if sinners try to entice you, do not consent. 11 If they say: “Come with us. Let us set an ambush to shed blood. We will lie hidden, waiting for innocent victims without cause. 12 We will swallow them alive as the Grave* does, Whole, like those going down to the pit. 13 Let us seize all their precious treasures; We will fill our houses with spoil. 14 You should join us,* And we will all share equally what we steal.”* 15 My son, do not follow them. Keep your feet off their path, 16 For their feet run to do evil; They hurry to shed blood. 17 It is surely in vain to spread a net in full sight of a bird. 18 That is why these lie in ambush to shed blood; They lie hidden to take the lives* of others. 19 These are the ways of those seeking dishonest profit, Which will take away the life* of those who obtain it. 20 True wisdom cries aloud in the street. It keeps raising its voice in the public squares. 21 At the corner* of the busy streets it calls out. At the entrances of the city gates it says: 22 “How long will you inexperienced ones love inexperience? How long will you ridiculers take pleasure in ridicule? And how long will you foolish ones hate knowledge? 23 Respond to my reproof.* Then I will pour out my spirit for you; I will make my words known to you. 24 Because I called out, but you kept refusing, I stretched out my hand, but no one was paying attention, 25 You kept neglecting all my advice And rejecting my reproof, 26 I also will laugh when disaster strikes you; I will mock when what you dread comes, 27 When what you dread comes like a storm, And your disaster arrives like a storm wind, When distress and trouble come upon you. 28 At that time they will keep calling me, but I will not answer; They will eagerly look for me, but they will not find me, 29 Because they hated knowledge, And they did not choose to fear Jehovah. 30 They refused my advice; They disrespected all my reproof. 31 So they will bear the consequences* of their way, And they will be glutted with their own counsel.* 32 For the waywardness of the inexperienced will kill them, And the complacency of fools will destroy them. 33 But the one listening to me will dwell in security And be undisturbed by the dread of calamity.”

2 My son, if you accept my sayings And treasure up my commandments,  2 By making your ear attentive to wisdom And inclining your heart to discernment;  3 Moreover, if you call out for understanding And raise your voice for discernment;  4 If you keep seeking for it as for silver, And you keep searching for it as for hidden treasures;  5 Then you will understand the fear of Jehovah, And you will find the knowledge of God.  6 For Jehovah himself gives wisdom; From his mouth come knowledge and discernment.  7 He treasures up practical wisdom for the upright; He is a shield for those walking in integrity.  8 He watches over the paths of justice, And he will guard the way of his loyal ones.  9 Then you will understand what is righteous and just and fair, The entire course of what is good. 10 When wisdom enters your heart And knowledge becomes pleasant to your soul,* 11 Thinking ability will keep watch over you, And discernment will safeguard you, 12 To save you from the bad course, From the man speaking perverse things, 13 From those leaving the upright paths To walk in the ways of darkness, 14 From those who rejoice in wrongdoing, Who find joy in the perverseness of evil, 15 Those whose paths are crooked And whose entire course is devious. 16 It will save you from the wayward* woman, From the smooth* words of the immoral* woman, 17 Who abandons the close companion* of her youth And forgets the covenant of her God; 18 For her house sinks down into death, And her paths* lead to those powerless in death. 19 None of those having relations with* her will return, Nor will they regain the pathways of life. 20 So follow the way of good people And stay on the paths of the righteous, 21 For only the upright will reside in the earth, And the blameless* will remain in it. 22 As for the wicked, they will be cut off from the earth, And the treacherous will be torn away from it.

3 My son, do not forget my teaching,* And may your heart observe my commandments,  2 Because they will add many days And years of life and peace to you.  3 Do not let loyal love and faithfulness* leave you. Tie them around your neck; Write them on the tablet of your heart;  4 Then you will find favor and good insight In the eyes of God and man.  5 Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, And do not rely* on your own understanding.  6 In all your ways take notice of him, And he will make your paths straight.  7 Do not become wise in your own eyes. Fear Jehovah and turn away from bad.  8 It will be a healing to your body* And refreshment for your bones.  9 Honor Jehovah with your valuable things, With the firstfruits* of all your produce;* 10 Then your storehouses will be completely filled, And your vats* will overflow with new wine. 11 My son, do not reject the discipline of Jehovah, And do not loathe his reproof, 12 For those whom Jehovah loves he reproves, Just as a father does a son in whom he delights. 13 Happy is the man who finds wisdom And the man who acquires discernment; 14 To gain it is better than gaining silver, And having it as profit is better than having gold. 15 It is more precious than corals;* Nothing you desire can compare to it. 16 Long life is in its right hand; Riches and glory are in its left hand. 17 Its ways are pleasant, And all its paths are peaceful. 18 It is a tree of life to those who take hold of it, And those who keep firm hold of it will be called happy. 19 Jehovah founded the earth in wisdom. He solidly established the heavens in discernment. 20 By his knowledge the watery deeps were split apart And the cloudy skies dripped with dew. 21 My son, do not lose sight of them.* Safeguard practical wisdom and thinking ability; 22 They will give you* life And be an adornment for your neck; 23 Then you will walk on your way in safety, And your foot will never stumble.* 24 When you lie down, you will have no fear; You will lie down, and your sleep will be pleasant. 25 You will not fear any sudden terror Nor the storm that is coming on the wicked. 26 For Jehovah will prove to be your source of confidence; He will keep your foot from being caught. 27 Do not withhold good from those to whom you should give it* If it is within your power* to help. 28 Do not say to your neighbor, “Go away; come back later! I will give it to you tomorrow,” If you can give it now. 29 Do not plot harm against your neighbor When he lives in a sense of security with you. 30 Do not quarrel with a man for no reason If he has done nothing bad to you. 31 Do not envy the violent man Nor choose any of his ways, 32 For Jehovah detests a devious person, But His close friendship is with the upright. 33 The curse of Jehovah is on the house of the wicked one, But he blesses the home of the righteous. 34 For he mocks those who ridicule, But he shows favor to the meek. 35 The wise will inherit honor, But the stupid ones glorify dishonor.

4 Listen, my sons, to the discipline of a father; Pay attention in order to gain understanding,  2 For I will give you good instruction; Do not forsake my teaching.*  3 I was a true son to my father And the one especially loved by my mother.  4 He taught me and said: “May your heart hold fast to my words. Keep my commandments and continue living.  5 Acquire wisdom, acquire understanding. Do not forget, and do not turn aside from what I say.  6 Do not forsake it, and it will protect you. Love it, and it will safeguard you.  7 Wisdom is the most important* thing, so acquire wisdom, And with all you acquire, acquire understanding.  8 Highly esteem it, and it will exalt you. It will honor you because you embrace it.  9 It will place an attractive wreath on your head; It will adorn you with a crown of beauty.” 10 Listen, my son, and accept my sayings, And the years of your life will be many. 11 I will instruct you in the way of wisdom; I will lead you in the tracks of uprightness. 12 When you walk, your steps will not be hindered; And if you run, you will not stumble. 13 Hold on to discipline; do not let it go. Safeguard it, for it means your life. 14 Do not enter the path of the wicked, And do not walk in the way of evil men. 15 Shun it, do not take it; Turn away from it, and pass it by. 16 For they cannot sleep unless they do what is bad. They are robbed of sleep unless they cause someone’s downfall. 17 They feed themselves with the bread of wickedness, And they drink the wine of violence. 18 But the path of the righteous is like the bright morning light That grows brighter and brighter until full daylight. 19 The way of the wicked is like the darkness; They do not know what makes them stumble. 20 My son, pay attention to my words; Listen carefully* to my sayings. 21 Do not lose sight of them; Keep them deep within your heart, 22 For they are life to those who find them And health to their whole body.* 23 Above all the things that you guard, safeguard your heart, For out of it are the sources of life. 24 Put crooked speech away from you, And keep devious talk far away from you. 25 Your eyes should look straight ahead, Yes, fix your gaze* straight ahead of you. 26 Smooth out* the course of your feet, And all your ways will be sure. 27 Do not incline to the right or the left. Turn your feet away from what is bad.

5 My son, pay attention to my wisdom. Listen carefully* to my discernment,  2 So that you may guard your thinking abilities And safeguard knowledge with your lips.  3 For the lips of a wayward* woman drip like a honeycomb, And her mouth is smoother than oil.  4 But in the end she is as bitter as wormwood And as sharp as a two-edged sword.  5 Her feet descend into death. Her steps lead straight to the Grave.*  6 She gives no thought to the path of life. Her course wanders, but she does not know where.  7 Now, my sons, listen to me And do not turn away from what I am saying.  8 Stay far away from her; Do not go near the entrance of her house,  9 So that you may not give your dignity to others Nor reap years of what is cruel; 10 So that strangers may not drain your resources* And what you labored for go to the house of a foreigner. 11 Otherwise, you will groan at the end of your life When your flesh and body waste away 12 And you say: “How I hated discipline! How my heart despised reproof! 13 I did not listen to the voice of my instructors Or pay attention to my teachers. 14 I have come to the brink of complete ruin In the midst of the entire congregation.”* 15 Drink water from your own cistern And flowing* water from your own well. 16 Should your springs be dispersed outside, Your streams of water in the public squares? 17 Let them be for you alone, And not for strangers with you. 18 May your own fountain* be blessed, And may you rejoice with the wife of your youth, 19 A loving doe, a graceful mountain goat.* Let her breasts satisfy* you at all times. May you be captivated by her love constantly. 20 So why, my son, should you be captivated by a wayward* woman Or embrace the bosom of an immoral* woman? 21 For the ways of man are before the eyes of Jehovah; He examines all his paths. 22 The wicked one is ensnared by his own errors, And he will be caught in the ropes of his own sin. 23 He will die for lack of discipline And go astray because of his excessive foolishness.

6 My son, if you have put up security* for your neighbor, If you have given your handshake* to a stranger,  2 If you have been ensnared by your promise, Caught by the words of your mouth,  3 Do this, my son, and free yourself, For you have fallen into the hand of your neighbor: Go and humble yourself and urgently plead with your neighbor.  4 Do not allow your eyes to sleep, Nor your eyelids to slumber.  5 Free yourself like a gazelle from the hunter’s hand, Like a bird from the hand of the birdcatcher.  6 Go to the ant, you lazy one; Observe its ways and become wise.  7 Although it has no commander, officer, or ruler,  8 It prepares its food in the summer, And it gathers its food supplies in the harvest.  9 How long, you lazy one, will you lie there? When will you rise up from your sleep? 10 A little sleep, a little slumbering, A little folding of the hands to rest, 11 And your poverty will come like a bandit, And your want like an armed man. 12 A useless and wicked man walks about with crooked speech; 13 He winks with his eye, signals with his foot, and motions with his fingers. 14 With a perverted heart, He is always scheming evil and spreading contentions. 15 Therefore, his disaster will come suddenly; In a moment he will be broken beyond healing. 16 There are six things that Jehovah hates; Yes, seven things that he* detests: 17 Haughty eyes, a lying tongue, and hands that shed innocent blood, 18 A heart plotting wicked schemes, and feet that run quickly to evil, 19 A false witness who lies with every breath, And anyone sowing contentions among brothers. 20 Observe, my son, the commandment of your father, And do not forsake the instruction* of your mother. 21 Always bind them around your heart; Tie them about your neck. 22 When you walk about, it will lead you; When you lie down, it will stand guard over you; And when you awaken, it will speak to you.* 23 For the commandment is a lamp, And the law is a light, And the reproofs of discipline are the way to life. 24 They will guard you against the bad woman, Against the seductive tongue of the immoral* woman. 25 Do not desire her beauty in your heart Or allow her to captivate you with her alluring eyes, 26 For because of a prostitute, a man is reduced to a loaf of bread, But the wife of another man preys on a precious life.* 27 Can a man rake fire to his chest and not burn his garments? 28 Or can a man walk on hot coals without scorching his feet? 29 It is the same with anyone having relations with his neighbor’s wife; No one who touches her will go unpunished. 30 People do not despise a thief If he steals to satisfy himself* when he is hungry. 31 Yet, when found, he will repay sevenfold; He will give up all the valuables of his house. 32 Anyone committing adultery with a woman is lacking good sense;* The one who does so brings ruin on himself.* 33 He will get only wounds and dishonor, And his disgrace will not be wiped away. 34 For jealousy makes a husband furious; He will show no compassion when he takes revenge. 35 He will accept no compensation;* He will not be appeased, no matter how large you make the gift.

Lit., “To know.”

Or “what is just.”

Or “fairness.”

Or “wise guidance.”

Or “a parable.”

Or “reverence for.”

Or “law.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “Throw in your lot with us.”

Or “share a common bag (purse).”

Or “souls.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “head.”

Or “Turn back when I reprove.”

Lit., “eat from the fruit.”

Or “schemes; plans.”

See Glossary.

Lit., “strange.” Evidently, one morally estranged from God.

Or “seductive.”

Lit., “foreign.” Evidently, one morally alienated from God.

Or “the husband.”

Lit., “tracks.”

Lit., “going in to.”

Or “the one who keeps integrity.”

Or “law.”

Or “truth.”

Lit., “lean.”

Lit., “navel.”

Or “very best.”

Or “income.”

Or “winepresses.”

See Glossary.

Evidently referring to God’s qualities mentioned in the previous verses.

Or “your soul.”

Or “strike against anything.”

Or “to whom it is owing.”

Or “within the power of your hand.”

Or “law.”

Or “the prime.”

Lit., “Incline your ear.”

Lit., “to all their flesh.”

Or “beaming eyes.”

Or possibly, “Carefully consider.”

Lit., “Incline your ear.”

Lit., “strange.” See Pr 2:16.

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “power.”

Lit., “In the midst of the assembly and the congregation.”

Or “fresh.”

Or “water source.”

Or “ibex.”

Or “intoxicate.”

Lit., “strange.” See Pr 2:16.

Lit., “foreign.” See Pr 2:16.

Lit., “gone surety.”

That is, in a pledge.

Or “his soul.”

Or “law.”

Or “instruct you.”

Lit., “foreign.” See Pr 2:16.

Or “soul.”

Or “fill his soul.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “ransom.”

^ (Prov. 6:20-35) Observe, my son, the commandment of your father, And do not forsake the instruction* of your mother. 21 Always bind them around your heart; Tie them about your neck. 22 When you walk about, it will lead you; When you lie down, it will stand guard over you; And when you awaken, it will speak to you.* 23 For the commandment is a lamp, And the law is a light, And the reproofs of discipline are the way to life. 24 They will guard you against the bad woman, Against the seductive tongue of the immoral* woman. 25 Do not desire her beauty in your heart Or allow her to captivate you with her alluring eyes, 26 For because of a prostitute, a man is reduced to a loaf of bread, But the wife of another man preys on a precious life.* 27 Can a man rake fire to his chest and not burn his garments? 28 Or can a man walk on hot coals without scorching his feet? 29 It is the same with anyone having relations with his neighbor’s wife; No one who touches her will go unpunished. 30 People do not despise a thief If he steals to satisfy himself* when he is hungry. 31 Yet, when found, he will repay sevenfold; He will give up all the valuables of his house. 32 Anyone committing adultery with a woman is lacking good sense;* The one who does so brings ruin on himself.* 33 He will get only wounds and dishonor, And his disgrace will not be wiped away. 34 For jealousy makes a husband furious; He will show no compassion when he takes revenge. 35 He will accept no compensation;* He will not be appeased, no matter how large you make the gift.

Or “law.”

Or “instruct you.”

Lit., “foreign.” See Pr 2:16.

Or “soul.”

Or “fill his soul.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “ransom.”

^ ***sn song 37 The Scriptures—Inspired of God***

Song 37

The Scriptures—Inspired of God

(2 Timothy 3:16, 17)

1. God’s Word is a shining light,

Guides our feet through earth’s dark night.

If we follow it faithfully,

Surely its truth will set us free.

2. That divine Word is inspired,

Teaches us what is required.

Help it gives, setting all things straight,

And for God’s discipline to wait.

3. By these Scriptures from above,

We have come to know God’s love.

Reading daily will make us wise,

Showing us how to gain life’s prize.

(See also [Ps. 119:105;][Prov. 4:13].)

^ (2 Tim. 3:16, 17) All Scripture is inspired of God and beneficial for teaching, for reproving, for setting things straight,* for disciplining in righteousness, 17 so that the man of God may be fully competent, completely equipped for every good work.

Or “correcting.”

^ (Ps. 119:105) Your word is a lamp to my foot, And a light for my path.

^ (Prov. 4:13) Hold on to discipline; do not let it go. Safeguard it, for it means your life.

^ ***w00 1/15 pp. 23-24 Cultivate Intimacy With Jehovah***

Cultivate Intimacy With Jehovah

“DRAW close to God, and he will draw close to you,” wrote the disciple James. ([James 4:8]) And the psalmist David sang: “The intimacy with Jehovah belongs to those fearful of him.” ([Psalm 25:14]) Clearly, Jehovah God wants us to have an intimate relationship with him. Yet, not everyone worshiping God and obeying his laws necessarily feels close to him.

What about you? Do you have a close personal relationship with God? Undoubtedly, you want to draw closer to him. How may we cultivate intimacy with God? What would this mean for us? The third chapter of the Bible book of Proverbs 3 provides answers.

Manifest Loving-Kindness and Trueness

King Solomon of ancient Israel commences the third chapter of Proverbs with the words: “My son, my law do not forget, and my commandments may your heart observe, because length of days and years of life and peace will be added to you.” (Proverbs 3:1, 2) Since Solomon wrote under divine inspiration, this fatherly advice is really coming from Jehovah God and is directed to us. We are counseled here to abide by God’s reminders—his law, or teaching, and his commandments—recorded in the Bible. If we do this, “length of days and years of life and peace will be added” to us. Yes, even now we can enjoy a peaceful life and can avoid pursuits that expose us to the danger of early death that often befalls evildoers. Moreover, we can entertain the hope of eternal life in a peaceful new world.—Proverbs 1:24-31;[2:21, 22].

Continuing, Solomon says: “May loving-kindness and trueness themselves not leave you. Tie them about your throat. Write them upon the tablet of your heart, and so find favor and good insight in the eyes of God and of earthling man.”—Proverbs 3:3, 4.

The original-language word for “loving-kindness” is alternatively rendered “loyal love” and entails fidelity, solidarity, and loyalty. Are we determined to remain attached to Jehovah come what may? Do we display loving-kindness in our relationships with fellow believers? Do we work to remain close to them? In day-to-day dealings with them, do we keep ‘the law of loving-kindness upon our tongue’ even under trying conditions?—Proverbs 31:26.

Being abundant in loving-kindness, Jehovah is “ready to forgive.” ([Psalm 86:5]) If we have repented of our past sins and are now making straight paths for our feet, we are assured that “seasons of refreshing” will come from Jehovah. ([Acts 3:19]) Should we not imitate our God by forgiving others of their trespasses?—Matthew 6:14, 15.

Jehovah is “the God of truth,” and he wants “trueness” from those seeking intimacy with him. ([Psalm 31:5]) Can we really expect Jehovah to be our Friend if we lead a double life—acting one way around Christian associates and another way when out of their sight—like “men of untruth” who hide what kind of people they are? ([Psalm 26:4]) How foolish that would be, since “all things are naked and openly exposed to the eyes” of Jehovah!—[Hebrews 4:13].

Loving-kindness and trueness are to be valued as a priceless necklace ‘tied about our throat,’ for they help us ‘find favor in the eyes of God and earthling man.’ We need not only to display these qualities outwardly but also to engrave them ‘on the tablet of our heart,’ making them an intrinsic part of our personality.

Cultivate Implicit Trust in Jehovah

The wise king continues: “Trust in Jehovah with all your heart and do not lean upon your own understanding. In all your ways take notice of him, and he himself will make your paths straight.”—Proverbs 3:5, 6.

Jehovah is certainly worthy of our complete trust. As the Creator, he is “vigorous in power” and is the Source of “dynamic energy.” (Isaiah 40:26,[29]) He is able to carry out all that he has purposed. Why, his very name literally means “He Causes to Become,” and it builds our confidence in his ability to fulfill what he has promised! The fact that “it is impossible for God to lie” makes him the very epitome of truth. ([Hebrews 6:18]) His dominant quality is love. ([1 John 4:8]) He is “righteous in all his ways and loyal in all his works.” ([Psalm 145:17]) If we cannot trust God, whom can we trust? Of course, to cultivate trust in him, we need to “taste and see that Jehovah is good” by applying what we learn from the Bible in our personal life and by reflecting upon the good that this produces.—[Psalm 34:8].

How may we ‘take notice of Jehovah in all our ways’? The inspired psalmist says: “I shall certainly meditate on all your activity, and with your dealings I will concern myself.” ([Psalm 77:12]) Since God is invisible, meditation on his great acts and on his dealings with his people is vital for cultivating intimacy with him.

Prayer is also an important way of taking notice of Jehovah. King David kept calling on Jehovah “all day long.” ([Psalm 86:3]) David often prayed through the night, as when he was a fugitive in the wilderness. (Psalm 63:6, 7) “Carry on prayer on every occasion in spirit,” exhorted the apostle Paul. (Ephesians 6:18) How often do we pray? Do we enjoy having personal heartfelt communication with God? When faced with trying situations, do we petition him for help? Do we prayerfully seek his guidance before making important decisions? Our sincere prayers to Jehovah endear us to him. And we have the assurance that he will listen to our prayer and ‘make our paths straight.’

How foolish it is to ‘lean upon our own understanding’ or that of prominent people in the world when we can place our complete confidence in Jehovah! “Do not become wise in your own eyes,” says Solomon. On the contrary, he admonishes: “Fear Jehovah and turn away from bad. May it become a healing to your navel and a refreshment to your bones.” (Proverbs 3:7, 8) The healthy fear of displeasing God ought to govern all our actions, thoughts, and emotions. Such reverential fear prevents us from doing what is bad and is spiritually healing and refreshing.

Give Jehovah Your Best

In what other way may we draw close to God? “Honor Jehovah with your valuable things and with the firstfruits of all your produce,” instructs the king. ([Proverbs 3:9]) To honor Jehovah means to show him high regard and to exalt him publicly by sharing in and supporting the public proclamation of his name. The valuable things with which we honor Jehovah are our time, our talents, our strength, and our material possessions. These must be the firstfruits—our very best. Should

^ (Jas. 4:8) Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.

^ (Ps. 25:14) Close friendship with Jehovah belongs to those who fear him, And he makes his covenant known to them.

^ (Prov. 3:1-35) My son, do not forget my teaching,* And may your heart observe my commandments,  2 Because they will add many days And years of life and peace to you.  3 Do not let loyal love and faithfulness* leave you. Tie them around your neck; Write them on the tablet of your heart;  4 Then you will find favor and good insight In the eyes of God and man.  5 Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, And do not rely* on your own understanding.  6 In all your ways take notice of him, And he will make your paths straight.  7 Do not become wise in your own eyes. Fear Jehovah and turn away from bad.  8 It will be a healing to your body* And refreshment for your bones.  9 Honor Jehovah with your valuable things, With the firstfruits* of all your produce;* 10 Then your storehouses will be completely filled, And your vats* will overflow with new wine. 11 My son, do not reject the discipline of Jehovah, And do not loathe his reproof, 12 For those whom Jehovah loves he reproves, Just as a father does a son in whom he delights. 13 Happy is the man who finds wisdom And the man who acquires discernment; 14 To gain it is better than gaining silver, And having it as profit is better than having gold. 15 It is more precious than corals;* Nothing you desire can compare to it. 16 Long life is in its right hand; Riches and glory are in its left hand. 17 Its ways are pleasant, And all its paths are peaceful. 18 It is a tree of life to those who take hold of it, And those who keep firm hold of it will be called happy. 19 Jehovah founded the earth in wisdom. He solidly established the heavens in discernment. 20 By his knowledge the watery deeps were split apart And the cloudy skies dripped with dew. 21 My son, do not lose sight of them.* Safeguard practical wisdom and thinking ability; 22 They will give you* life And be an adornment for your neck; 23 Then you will walk on your way in safety, And your foot will never stumble.* 24 When you lie down, you will have no fear; You will lie down, and your sleep will be pleasant. 25 You will not fear any sudden terror Nor the storm that is coming on the wicked. 26 For Jehovah will prove to be your source of confidence; He will keep your foot from being caught. 27 Do not withhold good from those to whom you should give it* If it is within your power* to help. 28 Do not say to your neighbor, “Go away; come back later! I will give it to you tomorrow,” If you can give it now. 29 Do not plot harm against your neighbor When he lives in a sense of security with you. 30 Do not quarrel with a man for no reason If he has done nothing bad to you. 31 Do not envy the violent man Nor choose any of his ways, 32 For Jehovah detests a devious person, But His close friendship is with the upright. 33 The curse of Jehovah is on the house of the wicked one, But he blesses the home of the righteous. 34 For he mocks those who ridicule, But he shows favor to the meek. 35 The wise will inherit honor, But the stupid ones glorify dishonor.

Or “law.”

Or “truth.”

Lit., “lean.”

Lit., “navel.”

Or “very best.”

Or “income.”

Or “winepresses.”

See Glossary.

Evidently referring to God’s qualities mentioned in the previous verses.

Or “your soul.”

Or “strike against anything.”

Or “to whom it is owing.”

Or “within the power of your hand.”

^ (Prov. 3:1-35) My son, do not forget my teaching,* And may your heart observe my commandments,  2 Because they will add many days And years of life and peace to you.  3 Do not let loyal love and faithfulness* leave you. Tie them around your neck; Write them on the tablet of your heart;  4 Then you will find favor and good insight In the eyes of God and man.  5 Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, And do not rely* on your own understanding.  6 In all your ways take notice of him, And he will make your paths straight.  7 Do not become wise in your own eyes. Fear Jehovah and turn away from bad.  8 It will be a healing to your body* And refreshment for your bones.  9 Honor Jehovah with your valuable things, With the firstfruits* of all your produce;* 10 Then your storehouses will be completely filled, And your vats* will overflow with new wine. 11 My son, do not reject the discipline of Jehovah, And do not loathe his reproof, 12 For those whom Jehovah loves he reproves, Just as a father does a son in whom he delights. 13 Happy is the man who finds wisdom And the man who acquires discernment; 14 To gain it is better than gaining silver, And having it as profit is better than having gold. 15 It is more precious than corals;* Nothing you desire can compare to it. 16 Long life is in its right hand; Riches and glory are in its left hand. 17 Its ways are pleasant, And all its paths are peaceful. 18 It is a tree of life to those who take hold of it, And those who keep firm hold of it will be called happy. 19 Jehovah founded the earth in wisdom. He solidly established the heavens in discernment. 20 By his knowledge the watery deeps were split apart And the cloudy skies dripped with dew. 21 My son, do not lose sight of them.* Safeguard practical wisdom and thinking ability; 22 They will give you* life And be an adornment for your neck; 23 Then you will walk on your way in safety, And your foot will never stumble.* 24 When you lie down, you will have no fear; You will lie down, and your sleep will be pleasant. 25 You will not fear any sudden terror Nor the storm that is coming on the wicked. 26 For Jehovah will prove to be your source of confidence; He will keep your foot from being caught. 27 Do not withhold good from those to whom you should give it* If it is within your power* to help. 28 Do not say to your neighbor, “Go away; come back later! I will give it to you tomorrow,” If you can give it now. 29 Do not plot harm against your neighbor When he lives in a sense of security with you. 30 Do not quarrel with a man for no reason If he has done nothing bad to you. 31 Do not envy the violent man Nor choose any of his ways, 32 For Jehovah detests a devious person, But His close friendship is with the upright. 33 The curse of Jehovah is on the house of the wicked one, But he blesses the home of the righteous. 34 For he mocks those who ridicule, But he shows favor to the meek. 35 The wise will inherit honor, But the stupid ones glorify dishonor.

Or “law.”

Or “truth.”

Lit., “lean.”

Lit., “navel.”

Or “very best.”

Or “income.”

Or “winepresses.”

See Glossary.

Evidently referring to God’s qualities mentioned in the previous verses.

Or “your soul.”

Or “strike against anything.”

Or “to whom it is owing.”

Or “within the power of your hand.”

^ (Prov. 3:1, 2) My son, do not forget my teaching,* And may your heart observe my commandments,  2 Because they will add many days And years of life and peace to you.

Or “law.”

^ (Prov. 1:24-31) Because I called out, but you kept refusing, I stretched out my hand, but no one was paying attention, 25 You kept neglecting all my advice And rejecting my reproof, 26 I also will laugh when disaster strikes you; I will mock when what you dread comes, 27 When what you dread comes like a storm, And your disaster arrives like a storm wind, When distress and trouble come upon you. 28 At that time they will keep calling me, but I will not answer; They will eagerly look for me, but they will not find me, 29 Because they hated knowledge, And they did not choose to fear Jehovah. 30 They refused my advice; They disrespected all my reproof. 31 So they will bear the consequences* of their way, And they will be glutted with their own counsel.*

Lit., “eat from the fruit.”

Or “schemes; plans.”

^ (Prov. 2:21, 22) For only the upright will reside in the earth, And the blameless* will remain in it. 22 As for the wicked, they will be cut off from the earth, And the treacherous will be torn away from it.

Or “the one who keeps integrity.”

^ (Prov. 3:3, 4) Do not let loyal love and faithfulness* leave you. Tie them around your neck; Write them on the tablet of your heart;  4 Then you will find favor and good insight In the eyes of God and man.

Or “truth.”

^ (Prov. 31:26) She opens her mouth in wisdom; The law of kindness* is on her tongue.

Or “Loving instruction; The law of loyal love.”

^ (Ps. 86:5) For you, O Jehovah, are good and ready to forgive; You abound in loyal love for all those who call on you.

^ (Acts 3:19) “Repent, therefore, and turn around so as to get your sins blotted out, so that seasons of refreshing may come from Jehovah himself*

Lit., “from the face of Jehovah.” See App. A5.

^ (Matt. 6:14, 15) “For if you forgive men their trespasses, your heavenly Father will also forgive you; 15 whereas if you do not forgive men their trespasses, neither will your Father forgive your trespasses.

^ (Ps. 31:5) Into your hand I entrust my spirit. You have redeemed me, O Jehovah, the God of truth.*

Or “the faithful God.”

^ (Ps. 26:4) I do not associate* with deceitful men, And I avoid those who hide what they are.*

Lit., “sit.”

Or “I do not mingle with hypocrites.”

^ (Heb. 4:13) And there is not a creation that is hidden from his sight, but all things are naked and openly exposed to the eyes of the one to whom we must give an account.

^ (Prov. 3:5, 6) Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, And do not rely* on your own understanding.  6 In all your ways take notice of him, And he will make your paths straight.

Lit., “lean.”

^ (Isa. 40:26) “Lift up your eyes to heaven and see. Who has created these things? It is the One who brings out their army by number; He calls them all by name. Because of his vast dynamic energy and his awe-inspiring power, Not one of them is missing.

^ (Isa. 40:29) He gives power to the tired one And full might to those lacking strength.*

Or “dynamic energy.”

^ (Heb. 6:18) in order that through two unchangeable things in which it is impossible for God to lie, we who have fled to the refuge may have strong encouragement to take firm hold of the hope set before us.

^ (1 John 4:8) Whoever does not love has not come to know God, because God is love.

^ (Ps. 145:17) Jehovah is righteous in all his ways And loyal in all that he does.

^ (Ps. 34:8) Taste and see that Jehovah is good; Happy is the man who takes refuge in him.

^ (Ps. 77:12) And I will meditate on all your activity And ponder over your dealings.

^ (Ps. 86:3) Show me favor, O Jehovah, For I call to you all day long.

^ (Ps. 63:6, 7) I remember you while upon my bed; I meditate on you during the watches of the night.  7 For you are my helper, And I shout joyfully in the shadow of your wings.

^ (Eph. 6:18) while with every form of prayer and supplication you carry on prayer on every occasion in spirit. And to that end stay awake, constantly making supplication in behalf of all the holy ones.

^ (Prov. 3:7, 8) Do not become wise in your own eyes. Fear Jehovah and turn away from bad.  8 It will be a healing to your body* And refreshment for your bones.

Lit., “navel.”

^ (Prov. 3:9) Honor Jehovah with your valuable things, With the firstfruits* of all your produce;*

Or “very best.”

Or “income.”

^ ***w00 1/15 p. 24 Cultivate Intimacy With Jehovah***

“men of untruth” who hide what kind of people they are? ([Psalm 26:4]) How foolish that would be, since “all things are naked and openly exposed to the eyes” of Jehovah!—[Hebrews 4:13].

Loving-kindness and trueness are to be valued as a priceless necklace ‘tied about our throat,’ for they help us ‘find favor in the eyes of God and earthling man.’ We need not only to display these qualities outwardly but also to engrave them ‘on the tablet of our heart,’ making them an intrinsic part of our personality.

Cultivate Implicit Trust in Jehovah

The wise king continues: “Trust in Jehovah with all your heart and do not lean upon your own understanding. In all your ways take notice of him, and he himself will make your paths straight.”—Proverbs 3:5, 6.

Jehovah is certainly worthy of our complete trust. As the Creator, he is “vigorous in power” and is the Source of “dynamic energy.” (Isaiah 40:26,[29]) He is able to carry out all that he has purposed. Why, his very name literally means “He Causes to Become,” and it builds our confidence in his ability to fulfill what he has promised! The fact that “it is impossible for God to lie” makes him the very epitome of truth. ([Hebrews 6:18]) His dominant quality is love. ([1 John 4:8]) He is “righteous in all his ways and loyal in all his works.” ([Psalm 145:17]) If we cannot trust God, whom can we trust? Of course, to cultivate trust in him, we need to “taste and see that Jehovah is good” by applying what we learn from the Bible in our personal life and by reflecting upon the good that this produces.—[Psalm 34:8].

How may we ‘take notice of Jehovah in all our ways’? The inspired psalmist says: “I shall certainly meditate on all your activity, and with your dealings I will concern myself.” ([Psalm 77:12]) Since God is invisible, meditation on his great acts and on his dealings with his people is vital for cultivating intimacy with him.

Prayer is also an important way of taking notice of Jehovah. King David kept calling on Jehovah “all day long.” ([Psalm 86:3]) David often prayed through the night, as when he was a fugitive in the wilderness. (Psalm 63:6, 7) “Carry on prayer on every occasion in spirit,” exhorted the apostle Paul. (Ephesians 6:18) How often do we pray? Do we enjoy having personal heartfelt communication with God? When faced with trying situations, do we petition him for help? Do we prayerfully seek his guidance before making important decisions? Our sincere prayers to Jehovah endear us to him. And we have the assurance that he will listen to our prayer and ‘make our paths straight.’

How foolish it is to ‘lean upon our own understanding’ or that of prominent people in the world when we can place our complete confidence in Jehovah! “Do not become wise in your own eyes,” says Solomon. On the contrary, he admonishes: “Fear Jehovah and turn away from bad. May it become a healing to your navel and a refreshment to your bones.” (Proverbs 3:7, 8) The healthy fear of displeasing God ought to govern all our actions, thoughts, and emotions. Such reverential fear prevents us from doing what is bad and is spiritually healing and refreshing.

Give Jehovah Your Best

In what other way may we draw close to God? “Honor Jehovah with your valuable things and with the firstfruits of all your produce,” instructs the king. ([Proverbs 3:9]) To honor Jehovah means to show him high regard and to exalt him publicly by sharing in and supporting the public proclamation of his name. The valuable things with which we honor Jehovah are our time, our talents, our strength, and our material possessions. These must be the firstfruits—our very best. Should

^ (Ps. 26:4) I do not associate* with deceitful men, And I avoid those who hide what they are.*

Lit., “sit.”

Or “I do not mingle with hypocrites.”

^ (Heb. 4:13) And there is not a creation that is hidden from his sight, but all things are naked and openly exposed to the eyes of the one to whom we must give an account.

^ (Prov. 3:5, 6) Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, And do not rely* on your own understanding.  6 In all your ways take notice of him, And he will make your paths straight.

Lit., “lean.”

^ (Isa. 40:26) “Lift up your eyes to heaven and see. Who has created these things? It is the One who brings out their army by number; He calls them all by name. Because of his vast dynamic energy and his awe-inspiring power, Not one of them is missing.

^ (Isa. 40:29) He gives power to the tired one And full might to those lacking strength.*

Or “dynamic energy.”

^ (Heb. 6:18) in order that through two unchangeable things in which it is impossible for God to lie, we who have fled to the refuge may have strong encouragement to take firm hold of the hope set before us.

^ (1 John 4:8) Whoever does not love has not come to know God, because God is love.

^ (Ps. 145:17) Jehovah is righteous in all his ways And loyal in all that he does.

^ (Ps. 34:8) Taste and see that Jehovah is good; Happy is the man who takes refuge in him.

^ (Ps. 77:12) And I will meditate on all your activity And ponder over your dealings.

^ (Ps. 86:3) Show me favor, O Jehovah, For I call to you all day long.

^ (Ps. 63:6, 7) I remember you while upon my bed; I meditate on you during the watches of the night.  7 For you are my helper, And I shout joyfully in the shadow of your wings.

^ (Eph. 6:18) while with every form of prayer and supplication you carry on prayer on every occasion in spirit. And to that end stay awake, constantly making supplication in behalf of all the holy ones.

^ (Prov. 3:7, 8) Do not become wise in your own eyes. Fear Jehovah and turn away from bad.  8 It will be a healing to your body* And refreshment for your bones.

Lit., “navel.”

^ (Prov. 3:9) Honor Jehovah with your valuable things, With the firstfruits* of all your produce;*

Or “very best.”

Or “income.”

^ ***w06 9/15 p. 17 par. 1 Highlights From the Book of Proverbs***

Scriptural Questions Answered:

1:7; 9:10—In what way is the fear of Jehovah “the beginning of knowledge” and “the start of wisdom”? Without the fear of Jehovah, there can be no knowledge, for he is the Creator of all things and the Author of the Scriptures. ([Romans 1:20;] 2 Timothy 3:16, 17) He is the very Source of all true knowledge. Hence, knowledge begins with the reverential fear of Jehovah. Godly fear is also the start of wisdom because there can be no wisdom without knowledge. Moreover, a person who lacks the fear of Jehovah will not use whatever knowledge he has to honor the Creator.

^ par. 1 (Prov. 1:7) The fear of* Jehovah is the beginning of knowledge. Only fools despise wisdom and discipline.

Or “reverence for.”

^ par. 1 (Prov. 9:10) The fear of Jehovah is the beginning of wisdom, And knowledge of the Most Holy One is understanding.

^ par. 1 (Rom. 1:20) For his invisible qualities are clearly seen from the world’s creation onward, because they are perceived by the things made, even his eternal power and Godship, so that they are inexcusable.

^ par. 1 (2 Tim. 3:16, 17) All Scripture is inspired of God and beneficial for teaching, for reproving, for setting things straight,* for disciplining in righteousness, 17 so that the man of God may be fully competent, completely equipped for every good work.

Or “correcting.”

^ ***it-2 p. 180 Knowledge***

Source of Knowledge. Jehovah is actually the basic Source of knowledge. Life, of course, is from him and life is essential for one’s having any knowledge. ([Ps 36:9;][Ac 17:25,][28]) Furthermore, God created all things, so human knowledge is based on a study of God’s handiwork. ([Re 4:11;][Ps 19:1, 2]) God also inspired his written Word, from which man can learn the divine will and purposes. ([2Ti 3:16, 17]) Thus the focal point of all true knowledge is Jehovah, and a person seeking it ought to have a fear of God that makes him careful not to incur Jehovah’s displeasure. Such fear is the beginning of knowledge. ([Pr 1:7]) Such godly fear puts one in position to gain accurate knowledge, whereas those who do not consider God readily draw wrong conclusions from the things that they observe.

^ (Ps. 36:9) With you is the source of life; By your light we can see light.

^ (Acts 17:25) nor is he served by human hands as if he needed anything, because he himself gives to all people life and breath and all things.

^ (Acts 17:28) For by him we have life and move and exist, even as some of your own poets have said, ‘For we are also his children.’*

Or “progeny.”

^ (Rev. 4:11) “You are worthy, Jehovah* our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power, because you created all things, and because of your will they came into existence and were created.”

See App. A5.

^ (Ps. 19:1, 2) The heavens are declaring the glory of God; The skies above* proclaim the work of his hands.  2 Day after day their speech bubbles forth, And night after night they reveal knowledge.

Or “expanse.”

^ (2 Tim. 3:16, 17) All Scripture is inspired of God and beneficial for teaching, for reproving, for setting things straight,* for disciplining in righteousness, 17 so that the man of God may be fully competent, completely equipped for every good work.

Or “correcting.”

^ (Prov. 1:7) The fear of* Jehovah is the beginning of knowledge. Only fools despise wisdom and discipline.

Or “reverence for.”

^ ***w00 9/15 pp. 25-26 Safeguard Your Name***

Safeguard Your Name

A MAN who designs beautiful buildings makes a name for himself as an expert architect. A young woman who excels scholastically becomes known as a brilliant student. Even a person who does nothing may make a name for himself as a sluggard. Emphasizing the value of making a favorable name, the Bible states: “A good name is more desirable than great riches, a good reputation than silver and gold.”—Proverbs 22:1, An American Translation.

A good name is developed by many small acts over a period of time. All that is needed to spoil it, though, is one foolish act. A single incident of sexual misconduct, for example, can sully a fine reputation. In the 6th chapter of the Bible book of Proverbs 6, King Solomon of ancient Israel provides a warning against attitudes and actions that can spoil our reputation as well as damage our relationship with Jehovah God. Among these are thoughtless pledges, laziness, deceit, and sexual immorality—essentially things that Jehovah hates. Giving heed to this advice will help us safeguard our good name.

Deliver Yourself From Foolish Pledges

The 6th chapter of Proverbs opens with the words: “My son, if you have gone surety for your fellowman, if you have given your handshake even to the stranger, if you have been ensnared by the sayings of your mouth, if you have been caught by the sayings of your mouth, take this action then, my son, and deliver yourself, for you have come into the palm of your fellowman: Go humble yourself and storm your fellowman with importunities.”—Proverbs 6:1-3.

This proverb counsels against getting involved in the business dealings of others, especially of strangers. Yes, the Israelites were to ‘sustain their brother who had grown poor and become financially weak.’ (Leviticus 25:35-38) But some enterprising Israelites got involved in speculative business ventures and obtained financial backing by convincing others to ‘go surety’ for them, thus making them liable for the debt. Similar situations may arise today. Financial institutions, for example, may require a cosigner before approving a loan they consider risky. How unwise to make such a commitment hastily in behalf of others! Why, it may entrap us financially, even giving us a bad name with banks and other creditors!

What if we find ourselves in the predicament of having taken an action that seemed wise at first but upon closer scrutiny appears foolish? The advice is to set aside pride and “storm your fellowman with importunities”—with persistent requests. We must do all we possibly can to set matters straight. One reference work points out: “Leave no stone unturned until you have agreed with your adversary and compromised the matter, so that your bond may not come against you or yours.” And this should be done without delay, for the king adds: “Do not give any sleep to your eyes, nor any slumber to your beaming eyes. Deliver yourself like a gazelle from the hand and like a bird from the hand of the birdcatcher.” (Proverbs 6:4, 5) Better it is to withdraw from an unwise commitment when possible than to be entrapped by it.

Be Industrious Like the Ant

“Go to the ant, you lazy one; see its ways and become wise,” admonishes Solomon. What wisdom can we gain from the ways of a little ant? The king answers: “Although it has no commander, officer or ruler, it prepares its food even in the summer; it has gathered its food supplies even in the harvest.”—Proverbs 6:6-8.

Ants are marvelously organized and remarkably cooperative with one another. Instinctively, they gather food supplies for the future. They have “no commander, officer or ruler.” True, the queen ant is there, but she is queen only in the sense that she lays eggs and is the mother of the colony. She gives no commands. Even with no foreman to drive them or supervisor to check on them, the ants keep tirelessly at their work.

Like the ant, should we not also be industrious? Working hard and striving to improve in our work is good for us whether we are being monitored or not. Yes, in school, at our place of employment, and while sharing in spiritual activities, we should do our best. As the ant benefits from its industriousness, so God wants us to ‘see good for all our hard work.’ (Ecclesiastes 3:13,[22;][5:18]) A clean conscience and personal satisfaction are the rewards of hard work.—Ecclesiastes 5:12.

Using two rhetorical questions, Solomon tries to awaken a slothful one from his indolence: “How long, you lazy one, will you keep lying down? When will you rise up from your sleep?” Mimicking him in speech, the king adds: “A little more sleep, a little more slumbering, a little more folding of the hands in lying down, and your poverty will certainly come just like some rover, and your want like an armed man.” (Proverbs 6:9-11) While the lazy one is supine, poverty overtakes him with the speed of a bandit, and scarcity attacks him like an armed man. The fields of a sluggard quickly become full of weeds and nettles. (Proverbs 24:30, 31) His business enterprise suffers losses in no time. For how long would an employer tolerate an idler? And can a student who is too lazy to study expect to do well in school?

Be Honest

Outlining yet another type of behavior that ruins a person’s reputation in the community and his relationship with God, Solomon continues: “A good-for-nothing man, a man of hurtfulness, is walking with crookedness of speech, winking with his eye, making signs with his foot, making indications with his fingers. Perverseness is in his heart. He is fabricating something bad all the time. He keeps sending out merely contentions.”—Proverbs 6:12-14.

This description is that of a deceiver. A liar usually tries to conceal his untruthfulness.

^ (Prov. 22:1) A good name* is to be chosen rather than great wealth; To be respected* is better than silver and gold.

Or “A good reputation.” Lit., “A name.”

Lit., “Favor.”

^ (Prov. 6:1-35) My son, if you have put up security* for your neighbor, If you have given your handshake* to a stranger,  2 If you have been ensnared by your promise, Caught by the words of your mouth,  3 Do this, my son, and free yourself, For you have fallen into the hand of your neighbor: Go and humble yourself and urgently plead with your neighbor.  4 Do not allow your eyes to sleep, Nor your eyelids to slumber.  5 Free yourself like a gazelle from the hunter’s hand, Like a bird from the hand of the birdcatcher.  6 Go to the ant, you lazy one; Observe its ways and become wise.  7 Although it has no commander, officer, or ruler,  8 It prepares its food in the summer, And it gathers its food supplies in the harvest.  9 How long, you lazy one, will you lie there? When will you rise up from your sleep? 10 A little sleep, a little slumbering, A little folding of the hands to rest, 11 And your poverty will come like a bandit, And your want like an armed man. 12 A useless and wicked man walks about with crooked speech; 13 He winks with his eye, signals with his foot, and motions with his fingers. 14 With a perverted heart, He is always scheming evil and spreading contentions. 15 Therefore, his disaster will come suddenly; In a moment he will be broken beyond healing. 16 There are six things that Jehovah hates; Yes, seven things that he* detests: 17 Haughty eyes, a lying tongue, and hands that shed innocent blood, 18 A heart plotting wicked schemes, and feet that run quickly to evil, 19 A false witness who lies with every breath, And anyone sowing contentions among brothers. 20 Observe, my son, the commandment of your father, And do not forsake the instruction* of your mother. 21 Always bind them around your heart; Tie them about your neck. 22 When you walk about, it will lead you; When you lie down, it will stand guard over you; And when you awaken, it will speak to you.* 23 For the commandment is a lamp, And the law is a light, And the reproofs of discipline are the way to life. 24 They will guard you against the bad woman, Against the seductive tongue of the immoral* woman. 25 Do not desire her beauty in your heart Or allow her to captivate you with her alluring eyes, 26 For because of a prostitute, a man is reduced to a loaf of bread, But the wife of another man preys on a precious life.* 27 Can a man rake fire to his chest and not burn his garments? 28 Or can a man walk on hot coals without scorching his feet? 29 It is the same with anyone having relations with his neighbor’s wife; No one who touches her will go unpunished. 30 People do not despise a thief If he steals to satisfy himself* when he is hungry. 31 Yet, when found, he will repay sevenfold; He will give up all the valuables of his house. 32 Anyone committing adultery with a woman is lacking good sense;* The one who does so brings ruin on himself.* 33 He will get only wounds and dishonor, And his disgrace will not be wiped away. 34 For jealousy makes a husband furious; He will show no compassion when he takes revenge. 35 He will accept no compensation;* He will not be appeased, no matter how large you make the gift.

Lit., “gone surety.”

That is, in a pledge.

Or “his soul.”

Or “law.”

Or “instruct you.”

Lit., “foreign.” See Pr 2:16.

Or “soul.”

Or “fill his soul.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “ransom.”

^ (Prov. 6:1-35) My son, if you have put up security* for your neighbor, If you have given your handshake* to a stranger,  2 If you have been ensnared by your promise, Caught by the words of your mouth,  3 Do this, my son, and free yourself, For you have fallen into the hand of your neighbor: Go and humble yourself and urgently plead with your neighbor.  4 Do not allow your eyes to sleep, Nor your eyelids to slumber.  5 Free yourself like a gazelle from the hunter’s hand, Like a bird from the hand of the birdcatcher.  6 Go to the ant, you lazy one; Observe its ways and become wise.  7 Although it has no commander, officer, or ruler,  8 It prepares its food in the summer, And it gathers its food supplies in the harvest.  9 How long, you lazy one, will you lie there? When will you rise up from your sleep? 10 A little sleep, a little slumbering, A little folding of the hands to rest, 11 And your poverty will come like a bandit, And your want like an armed man. 12 A useless and wicked man walks about with crooked speech; 13 He winks with his eye, signals with his foot, and motions with his fingers. 14 With a perverted heart, He is always scheming evil and spreading contentions. 15 Therefore, his disaster will come suddenly; In a moment he will be broken beyond healing. 16 There are six things that Jehovah hates; Yes, seven things that he* detests: 17 Haughty eyes, a lying tongue, and hands that shed innocent blood, 18 A heart plotting wicked schemes, and feet that run quickly to evil, 19 A false witness who lies with every breath, And anyone sowing contentions among brothers. 20 Observe, my son, the commandment of your father, And do not forsake the instruction* of your mother. 21 Always bind them around your heart; Tie them about your neck. 22 When you walk about, it will lead you; When you lie down, it will stand guard over you; And when you awaken, it will speak to you.* 23 For the commandment is a lamp, And the law is a light, And the reproofs of discipline are the way to life. 24 They will guard you against the bad woman, Against the seductive tongue of the immoral* woman. 25 Do not desire her beauty in your heart Or allow her to captivate you with her alluring eyes, 26 For because of a prostitute, a man is reduced to a loaf of bread, But the wife of another man preys on a precious life.* 27 Can a man rake fire to his chest and not burn his garments? 28 Or can a man walk on hot coals without scorching his feet? 29 It is the same with anyone having relations with his neighbor’s wife; No one who touches her will go unpunished. 30 People do not despise a thief If he steals to satisfy himself* when he is hungry. 31 Yet, when found, he will repay sevenfold; He will give up all the valuables of his house. 32 Anyone committing adultery with a woman is lacking good sense;* The one who does so brings ruin on himself.* 33 He will get only wounds and dishonor, And his disgrace will not be wiped away. 34 For jealousy makes a husband furious; He will show no compassion when he takes revenge. 35 He will accept no compensation;* He will not be appeased, no matter how large you make the gift.

Lit., “gone surety.”

That is, in a pledge.

Or “his soul.”

Or “law.”

Or “instruct you.”

Lit., “foreign.” See Pr 2:16.

Or “soul.”

Or “fill his soul.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “ransom.”

^ (Prov. 6:1-3) My son, if you have put up security* for your neighbor, If you have given your handshake* to a stranger,  2 If you have been ensnared by your promise, Caught by the words of your mouth,  3 Do this, my son, and free yourself, For you have fallen into the hand of your neighbor: Go and humble yourself and urgently plead with your neighbor.

Lit., “gone surety.”

That is, in a pledge.

^ (Lev. 25:35-38) “‘If your brother who is nearby becomes poor and cannot support himself, you must sustain him as you would a foreign resident and a settler, so that he may keep alive with you. 36 Do not take interest or make a profit* from him. You must be in fear of your God, and your brother will keep alive with you. 37 You must not lend him your money on interest or give out your food for profit. 38 I am Jehovah your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt to give you the land of Caʹnaan, to prove myself your God.

Or “take usury.”

^ (Prov. 6:4, 5) Do not allow your eyes to sleep, Nor your eyelids to slumber.  5 Free yourself like a gazelle from the hunter’s hand, Like a bird from the hand of the birdcatcher.

^ (Prov. 6:6-8) Go to the ant, you lazy one; Observe its ways and become wise.  7 Although it has no commander, officer, or ruler,  8 It prepares its food in the summer, And it gathers its food supplies in the harvest.

^ (Eccl. 3:13) also that everyone should eat and drink and find enjoyment for all his hard work. It is the gift of God.

^ (Eccl. 3:22) And I saw that there is nothing better than for a man to find enjoyment in his work, because that is his reward;* for who can enable him to see what will happen after he is gone?

Or “portion.”

^ (Eccl. 5:18) This is what I have seen to be good and proper: that one should eat and drink and find enjoyment for all the hard work at which he toils under the sun during the few days of life that the true God has given him, for that is his reward.*

Or “portion.”

^ (Eccl. 5:12) Sweet is the sleep of the one serving, whether he eats little or much, but the plenty belonging to the rich one does not permit him to sleep.

^ (Prov. 6:9-11) How long, you lazy one, will you lie there? When will you rise up from your sleep? 10 A little sleep, a little slumbering, A little folding of the hands to rest, 11 And your poverty will come like a bandit, And your want like an armed man.

^ (Prov. 24:30, 31) I passed by the field of the lazy one, By the vineyard of the man lacking good sense.* 31 I saw that it was overgrown with weeds; The ground was covered with nettles, And its stone wall was broken down.

Lit., “in want of heart.”

^ (Prov. 6:12-14) A useless and wicked man walks about with crooked speech; 13 He winks with his eye, signals with his foot, and motions with his fingers. 14 With a perverted heart, He is always scheming evil and spreading contentions.

^ ***sn song 107 Come to Jehovah’s Mountain***

Song 107

Come to Jehovah’s Mountain

([Isaiah 2:2-4])

1. Raise your eyes and behold,

Far above the highest hill.

There stands Jehovah’s mountain

Lifted up in this day.

People come from afar,

Ev’rywhere from sea to sea,

Calling to one another,

‘Come serve God and obey.’

Now the time has arrived

For the small, a great nation to be.

As we grow and we thrive,

God’s direction and blessing we see.

Millions now come to God

And accept his sov’reignty.

Loyal they vow to be

And from his side never stray.

2. Jesus gave the command

To go forth and preach the word.

Good news about the Kingdom

Reaches all men today.

Christ now rules from on high,

Urging all to take his side.

Meek ones who hear his voice

Let God’s Word show them the way.

What a joy to behold

How a great crowd continues to grow!

Yes, we all have a share,

Helping others Jehovah to know.

Let us lift up the voice,

Calling out for all to hear,

‘Come to Jehovah’s mountain,

Here forever to stay.’

(See also [Ps. 43:3;][99:9;][Isa. 60:22;][Acts 16:5].)

^ (Isa. 2:2-4) In the final part of the days,* The mountain of the house of Jehovah Will become firmly established above the top of the mountains, And it will be raised up above the hills, And to it all the nations will stream.  3 And many peoples will go and say: “Come, let us go up to the mountain of Jehovah, To the house of the God of Jacob. He will instruct us about his ways, And we will walk in his paths.” For law* will go out of Zion, And the word of Jehovah out of Jerusalem.  4 He will render judgment among the nations And set matters straight* respecting many peoples. They will beat their swords into plowshares And their spears into pruning shears. Nation will not lift up sword against nation, Nor will they learn war anymore.

Or “In the last days.”

Or “instruction.”

Or “correct matters.”

^ (Ps. 43:3) Send out your light and your truth. May these lead me; May they guide me to your holy mountain and to your grand tabernacle.

^ (Ps. 99:9) Exalt Jehovah our God And bow down* before his holy mountain, For Jehovah our God is holy.

Or “worship.”

^ (Isa. 60:22) The little one will become a thousand And the small one a mighty nation. I myself, Jehovah, will speed it up in its own time.”

^ (Acts 16:5) Then, indeed, the congregations continued to be made firm in the faith and to increase in number day by day.

^ ***yb16 p. 25-p. 27 The Light Keeps Getting Brighter***

HIGHLIGHTS OF THE PAST YEAR

The Light Keeps Getting Brighter

BECAUSE true worshippers acknowledge Jehovah as the Source of spiritual light, they eagerly pray that God’s ‘light and truth’ will lead and guide them. ([Ps. 43:3]) While the world is in dense spiritual darkness, the true God continues to shed light upon his people. As a result, their path “is like the bright morning light that grows brighter and brighter.” ([Prov. 4:18]) Increasing light from Jehovah continues to illuminate their way organizationally, doctrinally, and morally. What are some of our beliefs that have been clarified in recent years?

2012

“All these kingdoms”—[Dan. 2:44]

|

w12 6/15 p. 17

Mordecai and Esther “divide spoil”—[Gen. 49:27]

|

w12 1/1 p. 29

Ruin caused by “fierce-looking king”—Dan. 8:23, 24

|

w12 6/15 p. 16

Toes of image in Nebuchadnezzar’s dream—[Dan. 2:41-43]

|

w12 6/15 p. 16

When the seventh world power emerged

|

w12 6/15 pp. 15, 19

2013

“Faithful and discreet slave”—Matt. 24:45-47

|

w13 7/15 pp. 8, 20-25

“Evil slave”—Matt. 24:48-51

|

w13 7/15 p. 24

Anointed not to survive Armageddon on earth

|

w13 7/15 p. 5

‘Assyrian invades our land’—[Mic. 5:5]

|

w13 11/15 p. 20

Chosen ones gathered—[Matt. 24:31;][Mark 13:27]

|

w13 7/15 p. 5

Great tribulation

|

w13 7/15 pp. 3-8

Illustration of the wheat and the weeds—Matt. 13:24-30

|

w13 7/15 pp. 13-14

Jesus comes, arrives—Matt. chaps. 24 and[25]

|

w13 7/15 pp. 7-8, 24

Jesus inspects spiritual temple 1914-1919—[Mal. 3:1-4]

|

w13 7/15 pp. 11-12

Meaning of name Jehovah

|

New World Translation p. 1735

2014

Appointment of elders and ministerial servants

|

w14 11/15 pp. 28-29

Basis first-century Jews had for being “in expectation” of the Messiah—[Luke 3:15]

|

w14 2/15 pp. 26-27; w14 6/15 p. 22

Duration of cleansing of spiritual temple—[Mal. 3:1-4]

|

w14 11/15 p. 30

Marriage in the resurrection—Luke 20:34-36

|

w14 8/15 pp. 29-30

“Solid foundation of God”—[2 Tim. 2:19]

|

w14 7/15 pp. 8-9, 13

Two witnesses—Rev. chap. 11

|

w14 11/15 p. 30

2015

Gog of Magog—Ezek. chaps. 38 and[39]

|

w15 5/15 pp. 29-30

Head covering for sister conducting a Bible study

|

w15 2/15 p. 30

Illustration of the talents—Matt. 25:14-30

|

w15 3/15 pp. 20-24

Illustration of the ten virgins—Matt. 25:1-13

|

w15 3/15 pp. 13-16

Types and antitypes

|

w15 3/15 pp. 9-11, 17-18; w15 6/15 p. 32

^ par. 1 (Ps. 43:3) Send out your light and your truth. May these lead me; May they guide me to your holy mountain and to your grand tabernacle.

^ par. 1 (Prov. 4:18) But the path of the righteous is like the bright morning light That grows brighter and brighter until full daylight.

^ (Dan. 2:44) “In the days of those kings the God of heaven will set up a kingdom that will never be destroyed. And this kingdom will not be passed on to any other people. It will crush and put an end to all these kingdoms, and it alone will stand forever,

^ (Gen. 49:27) “Benjamin will keep on tearing like a wolf. In the morning he will eat the prey, and in the evening he will divide spoil.”

^ (Dan. 8:23, 24) “And in the final part of their kingdom, as the transgressors act to a completion,* a fierce-looking king who understands ambiguous sayings* will stand up. 24 His power will become great, but not through his own power. He will bring ruin in an extraordinary way,* and he will be successful and act effectively. He will bring mighty ones to ruin, also the people made up of the holy ones.

Or “have reached their limit.”

Or “who is skilled in intrigue.”

Or “bring terrible destruction.”

^ (Dan. 2:41-43) “And just as you saw the feet and the toes to be partly of clay of a potter and partly of iron, the kingdom will be divided, but some of the hardness of iron will be in it, just as you saw the iron mixed with soft clay. 42 And as the toes of the feet were partly of iron and partly of clay, so the kingdom will be partly strong and partly fragile. 43 Just as you saw iron mixed with soft clay, they will be mixed with the people;* but they will not stick together, one to the other, just as iron does not mix with clay.

Or “the offspring of mankind,” that is, the common people.

^ (Matt. 24:45-47) “Who really is the faithful and discreet* slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time? 46 Happy is that slave if his master on coming finds him doing so! 47 Truly I say to you, he will appoint him over all his belongings.

Or “wise.”

^ (Matt. 24:48-51) “But if ever that evil slave says in his heart, ‘My master is delaying,’ 49 and he starts to beat his fellow slaves and to eat and drink with the confirmed drunkards, 50 the master of that slave will come on a day that he does not expect and in an hour that he does not know, 51 and he will punish him with the greatest severity and will assign him his place with the hypocrites. There is where his weeping and the gnashing of his teeth will be.

^ (Mic. 5:5) And he will bring peace. Should the As·syrʹi·an invade our land and tread on our fortified towers, We will raise up against him seven shepherds, yes, eight princes* of mankind.

Or “leaders.”

^ (Matt. 24:31) And he will send out his angels with a great trumpet sound, and they will gather his chosen ones together from the four winds, from one extremity of the heavens to their other extremity.

^ (Mark 13:27) And then he will send out the angels and will gather his chosen ones together from the four winds, from earth’s extremity to heaven’s extremity.

^ (Matt. 13:24-30) He presented another illustration to them, saying: “The Kingdom of the heavens may be likened to a man who sowed fine seed in his field. 25 While men were sleeping, his enemy came and oversowed weeds in among the wheat and left. 26 When the stalk sprouted and produced fruit, then the weeds also appeared. 27 So the slaves of the master of the house came and said to him, ‘Master, did you not sow fine seed in your field? How, then, does it have weeds?’ 28 He said to them, ‘An enemy, a man, did this.’ The slaves said to him, ‘Do you want us, then, to go out and collect them?’ 29 He said, ‘No, for fear that while collecting the weeds, you uproot the wheat with them. 30 Let both grow together until the harvest, and in the harvest season, I will tell the reapers: First collect the weeds and bind them in bundles to burn them up; then gather the wheat into my storehouse.’”

^ (Matt. 24:1-51) Now as Jesus was departing from the temple, his disciples approached to show him the buildings of the temple. 2 In response he said to them: “Do you not see all these things? Truly I say to you, by no means will a stone be left here upon a stone and not be thrown down.” 3 While he was sitting on the Mount of Olives, the disciples approached him privately, saying: “Tell us, when will these things be, and what will be the sign of your presence* and of the conclusion of the system of things?”* 4 In answer Jesus said to them: “Look out that nobody misleads you, 5 for many will come on the basis of my name, saying, ‘I am the Christ,’ and will mislead many. 6 You are going to hear of wars and reports of wars. See that you are not alarmed, for these things must take place, but the end is not yet. 7 “For nation will rise against nation and kingdom against kingdom, and there will be food shortages and earthquakes in one place after another. 8 All these things are a beginning of pangs of distress. 9 “Then people will hand you over to tribulation and will kill you, and you will be hated by all the nations on account of my name. 10 Then, too, many will be stumbled and will betray one another and will hate one another. 11 Many false prophets will arise and mislead many; 12 and because of the increasing of lawlessness, the love of the greater number will grow cold. 13 But the one who has endured* to the end will be saved. 14 And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come. 15 “Therefore, when you catch sight of the disgusting thing that causes desolation, as spoken about by Daniel the prophet, standing in a holy place (let the reader use discernment), 16 then let those in Ju·deʹa begin fleeing to the mountains. 17 Let the man on the housetop not come down to take the goods out of his house, 18 and let the man in the field not return to pick up his outer garment. 19 Woe to the pregnant women and those nursing a baby in those days! 20 Keep praying that your flight may not occur in wintertime nor on the Sabbath day; 21 for then there will be great tribulation such as has not occurred since the world’s beginning until now, no, nor will occur again. 22 In fact, unless those days were cut short, no flesh would be saved; but on account of the chosen ones those days will be cut short. 23 “Then if anyone says to you, ‘Look! Here is the Christ,’ or, ‘There!’ do not believe it. 24 For false Christs and false prophets will arise and will perform great signs and wonders so as to mislead, if possible, even the chosen ones. 25 Look! I have forewarned you. 26 Therefore, if people say to you, ‘Look! He is in the wilderness,’ do not go out; ‘Look! He is in the inner rooms,’ do not believe it. 27 For just as the lightning comes out of the east and shines over to the west, so the presence* of the Son of man will be. 28 Wherever the carcass is, there the eagles will be gathered together. 29 “Immediately after the tribulation of those days, the sun will be darkened, and the moon will not give its light, and the stars will fall from heaven, and the powers of the heavens will be shaken. 30 Then the sign of the Son of man will appear in heaven, and all the tribes of the earth will beat themselves in grief, and they will see the Son of man coming on the clouds of heaven with power and great glory. 31 And he will send out his angels with a great trumpet sound, and they will gather his chosen ones together from the four winds, from one extremity of the heavens to their other extremity. 32 “Now learn this illustration from the fig tree: Just as soon as its young branch grows tender and sprouts its leaves, you know that summer is near. 33 Likewise also you, when you see all these things, know that he is near at the doors. 34 Truly I say to you that this generation will by no means pass away until all these things happen. 35 Heaven and earth will pass away, but my words will by no means pass away. 36 “Concerning that day and hour nobody knows, neither the angels of the heavens nor the Son, but only the Father. 37 For just as the days of Noah were, so the presence* of the Son of man will be. 38 For as they were in those days before the Flood, eating and drinking, men marrying and women being given in marriage, until the day that Noah entered into the ark, 39 and they took no note until the Flood came and swept them all away, so the presence of the Son of man will be. 40 Then two men will be in the field; one will be taken along and the other abandoned. 41 Two women will be grinding at the hand mill; one will be taken along and the other abandoned. 42 Keep on the watch, therefore, because you do not know on what day your Lord is coming. 43 “But know one thing: If the householder had known in what watch* the thief was coming, he would have kept awake and not allowed his house to be broken into. 44 On this account, you too prove yourselves ready, because the Son of man is coming at an hour that you do not think to be it. 45 “Who really is the faithful and discreet* slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time? 46 Happy is that slave if his master on coming finds him doing so! 47 Truly I say to you, he will appoint him over all his belongings. 48 “But if ever that evil slave says in his heart, ‘My master is delaying,’ 49 and he starts to beat his fellow slaves and to eat and drink with the confirmed drunkards, 50 the master of that slave will come on a day that he does not expect and in an hour that he does not know, 51 and he will punish him with the greatest severity and will assign him his place with the hypocrites. There is where his weeping and the gnashing of his teeth will be.

See Glossary.

Or “the age.” See Glossary.

Or “who endures.”

See Glossary.

See Glossary.

Or “at what time of night.”

Or “wise.”

^ (Matt. 25:1-46) “Then the Kingdom of the heavens may be likened to ten virgins who took their lamps and went out to meet the bridegroom. 2 Five of them were foolish, and five were discreet.* 3 For the foolish took their lamps but took no oil with them, 4 whereas the discreet took oil in their flasks along with their lamps. 5 While the bridegroom was delaying, they all became drowsy and fell asleep. 6 Right in the middle of the night there was a shout: ‘Here is the bridegroom! Go out to meet him.’ 7 Then all those virgins got up and put their lamps in order. 8 The foolish said to the discreet, ‘Give us some of your oil, because our lamps are about to go out.’ 9 The discreet answered, saying: ‘Perhaps there may not be enough for both us and you. Go instead to those who sell it, and buy some for yourselves.’ 10 While they were going off to buy it, the bridegroom came. The virgins who were ready went in with him to the marriage feast, and the door was shut. 11 Afterward, the rest of the virgins also came, saying, ‘Sir, Sir, open to us!’ 12 In answer he said, ‘I tell you the truth, I do not know you.’ 13 “Keep on the watch, therefore, because you know neither the day nor the hour. 14 “For it is just like a man about to travel abroad who summoned his slaves and entrusted his belongings to them. 15 He gave five talents* to one, two to another, and one to still another, to each according to his own ability, and he went abroad. 16 Immediately the one who received the five talents went and did business with them and gained five more. 17 Likewise, the one who received the two gained two more. 18 But the slave who received just one went off and dug in the ground and hid his master’s money.* 19 “After a long time, the master of those slaves came and settled accounts with them. 20 So the one who had received the five talents came forward and brought five additional talents, saying, ‘Master, you entrusted five talents to me; see, I gained five talents more.’ 21 His master said to him: ‘Well done, good and faithful slave! You were faithful over a few things. I will appoint you over many things. Enter into the joy of your master.’ 22 Next the one who had received the two talents came forward and said, ‘Master, you entrusted two talents to me; see, I gained two talents more.’ 23 His master said to him: ‘Well done, good and faithful slave! You were faithful over a few things. I will appoint you over many things. Enter into the joy of your master.’ 24 “Finally the slave who had received the one talent came forward and said: ‘Master, I knew you to be a demanding man, reaping where you did not sow and gathering where you did not winnow. 25 So I grew afraid and went and hid your talent in the ground. Here, you have what is yours.’ 26 In reply his master said to him: ‘Wicked and sluggish slave, you knew, did you, that I reaped where I did not sow and gathered where I did not winnow? 27 Well, then, you should have deposited my money* with the bankers, and on my coming I would have received it back with interest. 28 “‘Therefore, take the talent away from him and give it to the one who has the ten talents. 29 For to everyone who has, more will be given, and he will have an abundance. But the one who does not have, even what he has will be taken away from him. 30 And throw the good-for-nothing slave out into the darkness outside. There is where his weeping and the gnashing of his teeth will be.’ 31 “When the Son of man comes in his glory, and all the angels with him, then he will sit down on his glorious throne. 32 All the nations will be gathered before him, and he will separate people one from another, just as a shepherd separates the sheep from the goats. 33 And he will put the sheep on his right hand, but the goats on his left. 34 “Then the King will say to those on his right: ‘Come, you who have been blessed by my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you from the founding of the world. 35 For I became hungry and you gave me something to eat; I was thirsty and you gave me something to drink. I was a stranger and you received me hospitably; 36 naked* and you clothed me. I fell sick and you looked after me. I was in prison and you visited me.’ 37 Then the righteous ones will answer him with the words: ‘Lord, when did we see you hungry and feed you, or thirsty and give you something to drink? 38 When did we see you a stranger and receive you hospitably, or naked and clothe you? 39 When did we see you sick or in prison and visit you?’ 40 In reply the King will say to them, ‘Truly I say to you, to the extent that you did it to one of the least of these my brothers, you did it to me.’ 41 “Then he will say to those on his left: ‘Go away from me, you who have been cursed, into the everlasting fire prepared for the Devil and his angels. 42 For I became hungry, but you gave me nothing to eat; and I was thirsty, but you gave me nothing to drink. 43 I was a stranger, but you did not receive me hospitably; naked, but you did not clothe me; sick and in prison, but you did not look after me.’ 44 Then they too will answer with the words: ‘Lord, when did we see you hungry or thirsty or a stranger or naked or sick or in prison and did not minister to you?’ 45 Then he will answer them, saying: ‘Truly I say to you, to the extent that you did not do it to one of these least ones, you did not do it to me.’ 46 These will depart into everlasting cutting-off,* but the righteous ones into everlasting life.”

Or “wise.”

A Greek talent equaled 20.4 kg (654 oz t). See App. B14.

Lit., “silver.”

Lit., “silver.”

Or “not sufficiently dressed.”

That is, from life. Lit., “lopping off; pruning.”

^ (Mal. 3:1-4) “Look! I am sending my messenger, and he will clear up* a way before me. And suddenly the true Lord, whom you are seeking, will come to his temple; and the messenger of the covenant will come, in whom you take delight. Look! He will certainly come,” says Jehovah of armies. 2 “But who will endure the day of his coming, and who will be able to stand when he appears? For he will be like the fire of a refiner and like the lye* of laundrymen. 3 And he will sit as a refiner and cleanser of silver and will cleanse the sons of Leʹvi; and he will clarify* them like gold and like silver, and they will certainly become to Jehovah people presenting a gift offering in righteousness. 4 And the gift offering of Judah and of Jerusalem will actually be pleasing* to Jehovah, as in the days of long ago and as in the years of antiquity.

Or “prepare.”

Or “soap.”

Or “refine.”

Or “gratifying.”

^ (Luke 3:15) Now the people were in expectation and all of them were reasoning in their hearts about John, “May he perhaps be the Christ?”

^ (Mal. 3:1-4) “Look! I am sending my messenger, and he will clear up* a way before me. And suddenly the true Lord, whom you are seeking, will come to his temple; and the messenger of the covenant will come, in whom you take delight. Look! He will certainly come,” says Jehovah of armies. 2 “But who will endure the day of his coming, and who will be able to stand when he appears? For he will be like the fire of a refiner and like the lye* of laundrymen. 3 And he will sit as a refiner and cleanser of silver and will cleanse the sons of Leʹvi; and he will clarify* them like gold and like silver, and they will certainly become to Jehovah people presenting a gift offering in righteousness. 4 And the gift offering of Judah and of Jerusalem will actually be pleasing* to Jehovah, as in the days of long ago and as in the years of antiquity.

Or “prepare.”

Or “soap.”

Or “refine.”

Or “gratifying.”

^ (Luke 20:34-36) Jesus said to them: “The children of this system of things* marry and are given in marriage, 35 but those who have been counted worthy of gaining that system of things and the resurrection from the dead neither marry nor are given in marriage. 36 In fact, neither can they die anymore, for they are like the angels, and they are God’s children by being children of the resurrection.

Or “this age.” See Glossary.

^ (2 Tim. 2:19) Despite that, the solid foundation of God remains standing, having this seal, “Jehovah* knows those who belong to him,” and, “Let everyone calling on the name of Jehovah* renounce unrighteousness.”

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

^ (Rev. 11:1-19) And a reed like a rod* was given to me as he said: “Get up and measure the temple sanctuary of God and the altar and those worshipping in it. 2 But as for the courtyard that is outside the temple sanctuary, leave it out and do not measure it, because it has been given to the nations, and they will trample the holy city underfoot for 42 months. 3 I will cause my two witnesses to prophesy for 1,260 days dressed in sackcloth.” 4 These are symbolized by the two olive trees and the two lampstands and are standing before the Lord of the earth. 5 If anyone wants to harm them, fire comes out of their mouths and consumes their enemies. If anyone should want to harm them, this is how he must be killed. 6 These have the authority to shut up the sky* so that no rain may fall during the days of their prophesying, and they have authority over the waters to turn them into blood and to strike the earth with every sort of plague as often as they wish. 7 When they have finished their witnessing, the wild beast that ascends out of the abyss will wage war with them and conquer them and kill them. 8 And their corpses will be on the main street of the great city that is in a spiritual sense called Sodʹom and Egypt, where their Lord was also executed on the stake. 9 And those of the peoples and tribes and tongues* and nations will look at their corpses for three and a half days, and they do not allow their corpses to be laid in a tomb. 10 And those dwelling on the earth rejoice over them and celebrate, and they will send gifts to one another, because these two prophets tormented those dwelling on the earth. 11 After the three and a half days, spirit of life from God entered into them, and they stood on their feet, and great fear fell upon those who saw them. 12 And they heard a loud voice from heaven say to them: “Come up here.” And they went up into heaven in the cloud, and their enemies saw them.* 13 In that hour there was a great earthquake, and a tenth of the city fell; and 7,000 persons were killed by the earthquake, and the rest became frightened and gave glory to the God of heaven. 14 The second woe is past. Look! The third woe is coming quickly. 15 The seventh angel blew his trumpet. And there were loud voices in heaven, saying: “The kingdom of the world has become the Kingdom of our Lord and of his Christ, and he will rule as king forever and ever.” 16 And the 24 elders who were seated before God on their thrones fell upon their faces and worshipped God, 17 saying: “We thank you, Jehovah* God, the Almighty, the one who is and who was, because you have taken your great power and begun ruling as king. 18 But the nations became wrathful, and your own wrath came, and the appointed time came for the dead to be judged and to reward your slaves the prophets and the holy ones and those fearing your name, the small and the great, and to bring to ruin those ruining* the earth.” 19 And the temple sanctuary of God in heaven was opened, and the ark of his covenant was seen in his temple sanctuary. And there were flashes of lightning and voices and thunders and an earthquake and a great hail.

Or “a measuring rod.”

Or “heaven.”

Or “languages.”

Or “were looking on.”

See App. A5.

Or “to destroy those who are destroying.”

^ (Ezek. 38:1-23) The word of Jehovah again came to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, set your face against Gog of the land of Maʹgog, the head chieftain* of Meʹshech and Tuʹbal, and prophesy against him. 3 Say, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says: “Here I am against you, O Gog, head chieftain* of Meʹshech and Tuʹbal. 4 I will turn you around and put hooks in your jaws and bring you out with all your army, horses and horsemen, all of them clothed in splendor, a vast assembly with large shields and bucklers,* all of them wielding swords; 5 Persia, E·thi·oʹpi·a, and Put are with them, all of them with buckler and helmet; 6 Goʹmer and all its troops, the house of To·garʹmah from the remotest parts of the north, along with all its troops—many peoples are with you. 7 “‘“Be ready, prepare yourselves, you with all your armies that are assembled with you, and you will be their commander.* 8 “‘“You will be given attention* after many days. In the final part of the years you will invade the land whose people have been restored from the ravages of the sword, collected together out of many peoples onto the mountains of Israel, which had long been lying devastated. The inhabitants of this land were restored from the peoples, and all of them dwell in security. 9 You will come against them like a storm, and you will cover the land like clouds, you and all your troops and many peoples with you.”’ 10 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says: ‘In that day thoughts will come into your heart, and you will devise an evil plan. 11 You will say: “I will invade the land of unprotected settlements.* I will come against those living in security, without disturbance, all of them living in settlements unprotected by walls, bars, or gates.” 12 It will be to take much spoil and plunder, to attack the devastated places that are now inhabited and a people regathered from the nations, who are accumulating wealth and property, those who are living in the center of the earth. 13 “‘Sheʹba and Deʹdan, the merchants of Tarʹshish and all its warriors* will say to you: “Are you invading to get much spoil and plunder? Have you assembled your armies to carry off silver and gold, to take wealth and property, to seize a very great spoil?”’ 14 “So prophesy, son of man, and say to Gog, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says: “On that day when my people Israel are dwelling in security, will you not know it? 15 You will come from your place, from the remotest parts of the north, you and many peoples with you, all of them riding on horses, a great assembly, a vast army. 16 Like clouds covering the land, you will come against my people Israel. In the final part of the days I will bring you against my land so that the nations may know me when I sanctify myself through you before their eyes, O Gog.”’ 17 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says: ‘Are you not the same one I spoke about in the former days through my servants the prophets of Israel, who prophesied for many years that you would be brought against them?’ 18 “‘On that day, the day when Gog invades the land of Israel,’ declares the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘my great rage will flare up. 19 In my zeal, in the fire of my fury, I will speak; and in that day there will be a great earthquake in the land of Israel. 20 Because of me the fish of the sea, the birds of the sky, the wild beasts of the field, all the reptiles that creep on the ground, and all humans on the surface of the earth will tremble, and the mountains will be thrown down, and the cliffs will fall, and every wall will collapse to the ground.’ 21 “‘I will call for a sword against him on all my mountains,’ declares the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. ‘Every man’s sword will be against his own brother. 22 I will bring my judgment against him* with pestilence and bloodshed; and I will rain down a torrential downpour and hailstones and fire and sulfur on him and on his troops and on the many peoples with him. 23 And I will certainly magnify myself and sanctify myself and make myself known before the eyes of many nations; and they will have to know that I am Jehovah.’

Or “chief prince.”

Or “chief prince.”

A small shield, often carried by archers.

Lit., “guard.”

Or “summoned.”

Or “of open, rural country.”

Or “maned young lions.”

Or “I will bring myself into judgment with him.”

^ (Ezek. 39:1-29) “And you, son of man, prophesy against Gog, and tell him, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says: “I am against you, Gog, head chieftain* of Meʹshech and Tuʹbal. 2 I will turn you around and lead you and make you come up from the remotest parts of the north and bring you in upon the mountains of Israel. 3 I will knock your bow out of your left hand and make your arrows fall from your right hand. 4 On the mountains of Israel you will fall, you and all your troops and the peoples who will be with you. I will give you as food to all kinds of birds of prey and the wild beasts of the field.”’ 5 “‘You will fall on the open field, for I myself have spoken,’ declares the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. 6 “‘And I will send fire against Maʹgog and against those who are inhabiting the islands in security, and they will have to know that I am Jehovah. 7 I will make my holy name known among my people Israel, and I will not allow my holy name to be profaned any longer; and the nations will have to know that I am Jehovah, the Holy One in Israel.’ 8 “‘Yes, this is coming, and it will be done,’ declares the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. ‘This is the day I have spoken about. 9 The inhabitants of the cities of Israel will go out and make fires with the weapons—the bucklers* and shields, the bows and arrows, the war clubs* and lances. And they will use them to light fires for seven years. 10 They will not need to take wood from the field or gather firewood from the forests because they will use the weapons to light fires.’ “‘They will take spoil from those who despoiled them and plunder from those who had been plundering them,’ declares the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. 11 “‘On that day I will give Gog a burial place there in Israel, in the valley of those who travel east of the sea, and it will block the path of those passing through. That is where they will bury Gog and all his hordes, and they will call it the Valley of Hamon-Gog.* 12 The house of Israel will spend seven months burying them in order to cleanse the land. 13 All the people of the land will work at burying them, and this will bring them fame in the day that I glorify myself,’ declares the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. 14 “‘Men will be assigned to pass through the land constantly and bury the bodies left remaining on the surface of the earth, in order to cleanse it. They will continue the search for seven months. 15 When those who pass through the land see a human bone, they will set up a marker beside it. Then those assigned to do the burying will bury it in the Valley of Hamon-Gog. 16 And there will also be a city there named Ha·moʹnah.* And they will cleanse the land.’ 17 “As for you, son of man, this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says: ‘Say to every sort of bird and to all the wild beasts of the field, “Gather yourselves together and come. Gather all around my sacrifice that I am preparing for you, a great sacrifice on the mountains of Israel. You will eat flesh and drink blood. 18 You will eat the flesh of mighty ones and drink the blood of the chieftains of the earth—the rams, lambs, goats, and bulls—all the fattened animals of Baʹshan. 19 You will gorge yourselves on fat and drink blood until you are drunk from the sacrifice that I prepare for you.”’ 20 “‘At my table you will be filled up with horses and charioteers, mighty ones and all sorts of warriors,’ declares the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. 21 “‘I will display my glory among the nations, and all the nations will see the judgment that I have executed and the power* that I have demonstrated among them. 22 From that day on the house of Israel will have to know that I am Jehovah their God. 23 And the nations will have to know that the house of Israel went into exile because of their own error, because they were unfaithful to me. So I hid my face from them and handed them over to their enemies, and they all fell by the sword. 24 I dealt with them according to their uncleanness and their transgressions, and I hid my face from them.’ 25 “Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says: ‘I will restore the captives of Jacob and have mercy on the whole house of Israel; and I will zealously defend* my holy name. 26 After they have been humiliated for all their unfaithfulness toward me, they will dwell securely on their land, with no one to make them afraid. 27 When I bring them back from the peoples and collect them together from the lands of their enemies, I will also sanctify myself among them before the eyes of many nations.’ 28 “‘They will have to know that I am Jehovah their God when I send them into exile among the nations and then gather them back to their land, not leaving any of them behind. 29 I will not hide my face from them any longer, for I will pour out my spirit on the house of Israel,’ declares the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

Or “chief prince.”

A small shield, often carried by archers.

Or possibly, “handpikes,” a weapon with a pointed tip.

Or “the Valley of Gog’s Hordes.”

Meaning “Hordes.”

Lit., “hand.”

Lit., “show exclusive devotion for.”

^ (Matt. 25:14-30) “For it is just like a man about to travel abroad who summoned his slaves and entrusted his belongings to them. 15 He gave five talents* to one, two to another, and one to still another, to each according to his own ability, and he went abroad. 16 Immediately the one who received the five talents went and did business with them and gained five more. 17 Likewise, the one who received the two gained two more. 18 But the slave who received just one went off and dug in the ground and hid his master’s money.* 19 “After a long time, the master of those slaves came and settled accounts with them. 20 So the one who had received the five talents came forward and brought five additional talents, saying, ‘Master, you entrusted five talents to me; see, I gained five talents more.’ 21 His master said to him: ‘Well done, good and faithful slave! You were faithful over a few things. I will appoint you over many things. Enter into the joy of your master.’ 22 Next the one who had received the two talents came forward and said, ‘Master, you entrusted two talents to me; see, I gained two talents more.’ 23 His master said to him: ‘Well done, good and faithful slave! You were faithful over a few things. I will appoint you over many things. Enter into the joy of your master.’ 24 “Finally the slave who had received the one talent came forward and said: ‘Master, I knew you to be a demanding man, reaping where you did not sow and gathering where you did not winnow. 25 So I grew afraid and went and hid your talent in the ground. Here, you have what is yours.’ 26 In reply his master said to him: ‘Wicked and sluggish slave, you knew, did you, that I reaped where I did not sow and gathered where I did not winnow? 27 Well, then, you should have deposited my money* with the bankers, and on my coming I would have received it back with interest. 28 “‘Therefore, take the talent away from him and give it to the one who has the ten talents. 29 For to everyone who has, more will be given, and he will have an abundance. But the one who does not have, even what he has will be taken away from him. 30 And throw the good-for-nothing slave out into the darkness outside. There is where his weeping and the gnashing of his teeth will be.’

A Greek talent equaled 20.4 kg (654 oz t). See App. B14.

Lit., “silver.”

Lit., “silver.”

^ (Matt. 25:1-13) “Then the Kingdom of the heavens may be likened to ten virgins who took their lamps and went out to meet the bridegroom. 2 Five of them were foolish, and five were discreet.* 3 For the foolish took their lamps but took no oil with them, 4 whereas the discreet took oil in their flasks along with their lamps. 5 While the bridegroom was delaying, they all became drowsy and fell asleep. 6 Right in the middle of the night there was a shout: ‘Here is the bridegroom! Go out to meet him.’ 7 Then all those virgins got up and put their lamps in order. 8 The foolish said to the discreet, ‘Give us some of your oil, because our lamps are about to go out.’ 9 The discreet answered, saying: ‘Perhaps there may not be enough for both us and you. Go instead to those who sell it, and buy some for yourselves.’ 10 While they were going off to buy it, the bridegroom came. The virgins who were ready went in with him to the marriage feast, and the door was shut. 11 Afterward, the rest of the virgins also came, saying, ‘Sir, Sir, open to us!’ 12 In answer he said, ‘I tell you the truth, I do not know you.’ 13 “Keep on the watch, therefore, because you know neither the day nor the hour.

Or “wise.”

^ ***kr pp. 13-16 The Kingdom Is Born in Heaven***

1, 2. What was the greatest event ever to occur in world history, and why is it not surprising that it went unseen by human eyes?

DO YOU ever wonder what it might have been like to live during some great turning point in history? Many do. But consider: If you had lived in such a momentous time, would you have personally witnessed the key events that brought about change? Perhaps not. Events that spell doom for old regimes and fill the pages of history books often take place out of the public eye. In a sense, much of history unfolds behind closed doors—in throne rooms, in private council chambers, or in government offices. Nonetheless, such changes affect millions of lives.

2 What about the greatest event ever to occur in the history of the world? That event has touched millions of lives. Yet, it took place out of human view. We refer, of course, to the birth in heaven of God’s Kingdom, the long-promised Messianic government that will soon bring this whole world system to its end. (Read Daniel 2:34, 35, 44, 45.) Since humans did not witness that momentous birth, should we conclude that Jehovah hid the event from mankind? Or, rather, did he prepare his loyal people for it beforehand? Let us see.

“My Messenger . . . Will Clear Up a Way Before Me”

3-5. (a) Who was “the messenger of the covenant” mentioned at [Malachi 3:1]? (b) What would happen before “the messenger of the covenant” would come to the temple?

3 From ancient times, Jehovah purposed to prepare his people for the birth of the Messianic Kingdom. For instance, consider the prophecy of [Malachi 3:1]: “Look! I am sending my messenger, and he will clear up a way before me. And suddenly the true Lord, whom you are seeking, will come to his temple; and the messenger of the covenant will come, in whom you take delight.”

4 In the modern-day fulfillment, when did Jehovah, “the true Lord,” come to inspect those who were serving in the earthly courtyard of his spiritual temple? The prophecy explains that Jehovah would come with “the messenger of the covenant.” Who was that? None other than the Messianic King, Jesus Christ! ([Luke 1:68-73]) As the newly installed Ruler, he would inspect and refine God’s people on earth.—[1 Pet. 4:17].

5 Who, though, was the other “messenger,” the first one mentioned at [Malachi 3:1]? This prophetic figure would be on the scene well before the Messianic King’s presence. In the decades before 1914, did anyone “clear up a way” before the Messianic King?

6. Who acted as the foretold “messenger” that came first to prepare God’s people for the events ahead?

6 Throughout this publication, we will find answers to such questions in the thrilling history of Jehovah’s modern-day people. This history shows that in the latter part of the 19th century, one small group of faithful people was emerging as the only body of genuine Christians in a vast field of imitations. That group came to be known as the Bible Students. Those taking the lead among them—Charles T. Russell and his close associates—did, indeed, act as the foretold “messenger,” giving spiritual direction to God’s people and preparing them for the events ahead. Let us consider four ways in which the “messenger” did so.

Worshipping in Truth

7, 8. (a) During the 1800’s, who began to expose the falseness of the immortality of the soul doctrine? (b) C. T. Russell and his close associates exposed what other teachings as false?

7 Those Bible Students studied prayerfully; they agreed on, collected together, and published clear doctrinal truths. For centuries, the world of Christendom had been enveloped in spiritual darkness; many of its teachings were rooted in paganism. A prime example is the doctrine of the immortality of the soul. During the 1800’s, though, a few sincere students of the Bible scrutinized that teaching and saw that it had no support in God’s Word. Henry Grew, George Stetson, and George Storrs wrote and lectured boldly, exposing that satanic lie.* Their work, in turn, had a profound impact on C. T. Russell and his close associates.

8 The little group of Bible Students found that other doctrines linked to the immortality of the soul were likewise confusing and false—for example, the teaching that all good people go to heaven or that God torments the immortal souls of the wicked in eternal hellfire. Russell and his close associates boldly exposed those lies in numerous articles, books, pamphlets, tracts, and published sermons.

9. How did Zion’s Watch Tower expose as false the Trinity doctrine?

9 Likewise, the Bible Students exposed as false the widely revered Trinity doctrine. In 1887, Zion’s Watch Tower remarked: “The Scriptures are very clear concerning the distinct individuality and exact relationship of Jehovah and our Lord Jesus.” The article then noted how amazing it was that “the idea of a triune God—three Gods in one, and at the same time, one God in three—should ever have gained prominence and general acceptance. But the fact that it is so, only goes to show how soundly the church slept while the enemy bound her in the chains of error.”

10. How did the Watch Tower point to 1914 as a marked year?

10 As its full title suggested, the journal Zion’s Watch Tower and Herald of Christ’s Presence was deeply concerned with prophecies pertaining to Christ’s presence. The faithful anointed writers who contributed to that journal saw that Daniel’s prophecy regarding the “seven times” had a bearing on the timing of the fulfillment of God’s purposes regarding the Messianic Kingdom. As early as the 1870’s, they pointed to 1914 as the year when those seven times would end. ([Dan. 4:25;][Luke 21:24]) Although our brothers of that era did not yet grasp the full significance of that marked year, they proclaimed what they knew far and wide, with long-lasting effects.

11, 12. (a) To whom did Brother Russell give credit for what he taught? (b) How important was the work carried out by Russell and his associates in the decades prior to 1914?

11 Neither Russell nor his faithful associates claimed credit for uncovering and grasping those vital spiritual truths. Russell gave much credit to others who had come before him. Above all, he gave credit to Jehovah God, the one responsible for teaching His people what they need to know when they need to know it. Clearly, Jehovah did bless the efforts of Russell and his associates to sift out truth from falsehood. As the years passed, they stood ever more apart and distinct from Christendom.

12 The work those faithful men did in championing doctrinal truth in the decades before 1914 was simply amazing! Looking back, The Watch Tower and Herald of Christ’s Presence of November 1, 1917, commented: “Millions of people today find themselves free from the burden of fear, imposed upon them by the teachings of hell fire and other false doctrines . . . The tide of Truth, which began more than forty years ago, is still steadily rising and will continue to rise until it fills the whole earth; and its opponents might as well try to sweep back with an ordinary broom the waves of a mighty ocean as to prevent the Truth from spreading throughout the earth.”

^ par. 2 (Dan. 2:34, 35) You looked on until a stone was cut out, not by hands, and it struck the image on its feet of iron and of clay and crushed them. 35 At that time the iron, the clay, the copper, the silver, and the gold were, all together, crushed and became like the chaff from the summer threshing floor, and the wind carried them away so that not a trace of them could be found. But the stone that struck the image became a large mountain, and it filled the whole earth.

^ par. 2 (Dan. 2:44, 45) “In the days of those kings the God of heaven will set up a kingdom that will never be destroyed. And this kingdom will not be passed on to any other people. It will crush and put an end to all these kingdoms, and it alone will stand forever, 45 just as you saw that out of the mountain a stone was cut not by hands, and that it crushed the iron, the copper, the clay, the silver, and the gold. The Grand God has made known to the king what will happen in the future. The dream is true, and its interpretation is trustworthy.”

^ (Mal. 3:1) “Look! I am sending my messenger, and he will clear up* a way before me. And suddenly the true Lord, whom you are seeking, will come to his temple; and the messenger of the covenant will come, in whom you take delight. Look! He will certainly come,” says Jehovah of armies.

Or “prepare.”

^ par. 3 (Mal. 3:1) “Look! I am sending my messenger, and he will clear up* a way before me. And suddenly the true Lord, whom you are seeking, will come to his temple; and the messenger of the covenant will come, in whom you take delight. Look! He will certainly come,” says Jehovah of armies.

Or “prepare.”

^ par. 4 (Luke 1:68-73) “Let Jehovah* be praised, the God of Israel, because he has turned his attention to his people and has brought them deliverance. 69 And he has raised up a horn of salvation* for us in the house of David his servant, 70 just as he has spoken through the mouth of his holy prophets from of old, 71 of a salvation from our enemies and from the hand of all those hating us; 72 to show mercy in connection with our forefathers and to call to mind his holy covenant, 73 the oath that he swore to Abraham our forefather,

See App. A5.

Or “a powerful savior.” See Glossary, “Horn.”

^ par. 4 (1 Pet. 4:17) For it is the appointed time for the judgment to start with the house of God. Now if it starts first with us, what will the outcome be for those who are not obedient to the good news of God?

^ par. 5 (Mal. 3:1) “Look! I am sending my messenger, and he will clear up* a way before me. And suddenly the true Lord, whom you are seeking, will come to his temple; and the messenger of the covenant will come, in whom you take delight. Look! He will certainly come,” says Jehovah of armies.

Or “prepare.”

^ par. 10 (Dan. 4:25) You will be driven away from among men, and your dwelling will be with the beasts of the field, and you will be given vegetation to eat just like bulls; and you will become wet with the dew of the heavens, and seven times will pass over you, until you know that the Most High is Ruler in the kingdom of mankind and that he grants it to whomever he wants.

^ par. 10 (Luke 21:24) And they will fall by the edge of the sword and be led captive into all the nations; and Jerusalem will be trampled on by the nations* until the appointed times of the nations* are fulfilled.

Or “Gentiles.”

Or “Gentiles.”

^ par. 7 To learn more about Grew, Stetson, and Storrs, see the book Jehovah’s Witnesses—Proclaimers of God’s Kingdom, pages 45-46.

^ ***snnw song 143 Light in a Darkened World***

Song 143

Light in a Darkened World

Download:

Lyrics Only

Lead Sheet

(2 Corinthians 4:6)

In these days, dark and lawless days,

Shines a light we can see.

Like the dawn of another day

That will soon come to be.

(CHORUS)

Shining through the darkness,

Ours is a message so bright.

It offers hope and light—

Sparkling like the daylight,

Bringing tomorrow in sight—

So ends the night.

Those who sleep need awakening

As the time ebbs away.

We give hope and encouragement.

For their future we’ll pray.

(CHORUS)

Shining through the darkness,

Ours is a message so bright.

It offers hope and light—

Sparkling like the daylight,

Bringing tomorrow in sight—

So ends the night.

(See also [John 3:19;][8:12;] Rom. 13:11, 12;[1 Pet. 2:9].)

^ (2 Cor. 4:6) For God is the one who said: “Let the light shine out of darkness,” and he has shone on our hearts to illuminate them with the glorious knowledge of God by the face of Christ.

^ (John 3:19) Now this is the basis for judgment: that the light has come into the world, but men have loved the darkness rather than the light, for their works were wicked.

^ (John 8:12) Then Jesus spoke again to them, saying: “I am the light of the world. Whoever follows me will by no means walk in darkness, but will possess the light of life.”

^ (Rom. 13:11, 12) And do this because you know the season, that it is already the hour for you to awake from sleep, for now our salvation is nearer than at the time when we became believers. 12 The night is well along; the day has drawn near. Let us therefore throw off the works belonging to darkness and let us put on the weapons of the light.

^ (1 Pet. 2:9) But you are “a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a people for special possession, that you should declare abroad the excellencies”* of the One who called you out of darkness into his wonderful light.

Lit., “the virtues,” that is, his praiseworthy qualities and deeds.

^ (Prov. 1:1-6:35) The proverbs of Solʹo·mon, the son of David, the king of Israel:  2 To learn* wisdom and discipline; To understand wise sayings;  3 To acquire the discipline that gives insight, Righteousness, good judgment,* and uprightness;*  4 To impart shrewdness to the inexperienced; To give a young man knowledge and thinking ability.  5 A wise person listens and takes in more instruction; A man of understanding acquires skillful direction*  6 To understand a proverb and a puzzling saying,* The words of the wise and their riddles.  7 The fear of* Jehovah is the beginning of knowledge. Only fools despise wisdom and discipline.  8 Listen, my son, to the discipline of your father, And do not forsake the instruction* of your mother.  9 They are an attractive wreath for your head And a fine ornament for your neck. 10 My son, if sinners try to entice you, do not consent. 11 If they say: “Come with us. Let us set an ambush to shed blood. We will lie hidden, waiting for innocent victims without cause. 12 We will swallow them alive as the Grave* does, Whole, like those going down to the pit. 13 Let us seize all their precious treasures; We will fill our houses with spoil. 14 You should join us,* And we will all share equally what we steal.”* 15 My son, do not follow them. Keep your feet off their path, 16 For their feet run to do evil; They hurry to shed blood. 17 It is surely in vain to spread a net in full sight of a bird. 18 That is why these lie in ambush to shed blood; They lie hidden to take the lives* of others. 19 These are the ways of those seeking dishonest profit, Which will take away the life* of those who obtain it. 20 True wisdom cries aloud in the street. It keeps raising its voice in the public squares. 21 At the corner* of the busy streets it calls out. At the entrances of the city gates it says: 22 “How long will you inexperienced ones love inexperience? How long will you ridiculers take pleasure in ridicule? And how long will you foolish ones hate knowledge? 23 Respond to my reproof.* Then I will pour out my spirit for you; I will make my words known to you. 24 Because I called out, but you kept refusing, I stretched out my hand, but no one was paying attention, 25 You kept neglecting all my advice And rejecting my reproof, 26 I also will laugh when disaster strikes you; I will mock when what you dread comes, 27 When what you dread comes like a storm, And your disaster arrives like a storm wind, When distress and trouble come upon you. 28 At that time they will keep calling me, but I will not answer; They will eagerly look for me, but they will not find me, 29 Because they hated knowledge, And they did not choose to fear Jehovah. 30 They refused my advice; They disrespected all my reproof. 31 So they will bear the consequences* of their way, And they will be glutted with their own counsel.* 32 For the waywardness of the inexperienced will kill them, And the complacency of fools will destroy them. 33 But the one listening to me will dwell in security And be undisturbed by the dread of calamity.”

2 My son, if you accept my sayings And treasure up my commandments,  2 By making your ear attentive to wisdom And inclining your heart to discernment;  3 Moreover, if you call out for understanding And raise your voice for discernment;  4 If you keep seeking for it as for silver, And you keep searching for it as for hidden treasures;  5 Then you will understand the fear of Jehovah, And you will find the knowledge of God.  6 For Jehovah himself gives wisdom; From his mouth come knowledge and discernment.  7 He treasures up practical wisdom for the upright; He is a shield for those walking in integrity.  8 He watches over the paths of justice, And he will guard the way of his loyal ones.  9 Then you will understand what is righteous and just and fair, The entire course of what is good. 10 When wisdom enters your heart And knowledge becomes pleasant to your soul,* 11 Thinking ability will keep watch over you, And discernment will safeguard you, 12 To save you from the bad course, From the man speaking perverse things, 13 From those leaving the upright paths To walk in the ways of darkness, 14 From those who rejoice in wrongdoing, Who find joy in the perverseness of evil, 15 Those whose paths are crooked And whose entire course is devious. 16 It will save you from the wayward* woman, From the smooth* words of the immoral* woman, 17 Who abandons the close companion* of her youth And forgets the covenant of her God; 18 For her house sinks down into death, And her paths* lead to those powerless in death. 19 None of those having relations with* her will return, Nor will they regain the pathways of life. 20 So follow the way of good people And stay on the paths of the righteous, 21 For only the upright will reside in the earth, And the blameless* will remain in it. 22 As for the wicked, they will be cut off from the earth, And the treacherous will be torn away from it.

3 My son, do not forget my teaching,* And may your heart observe my commandments,  2 Because they will add many days And years of life and peace to you.  3 Do not let loyal love and faithfulness* leave you. Tie them around your neck; Write them on the tablet of your heart;  4 Then you will find favor and good insight In the eyes of God and man.  5 Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, And do not rely* on your own understanding.  6 In all your ways take notice of him, And he will make your paths straight.  7 Do not become wise in your own eyes. Fear Jehovah and turn away from bad.  8 It will be a healing to your body* And refreshment for your bones.  9 Honor Jehovah with your valuable things, With the firstfruits* of all your produce;* 10 Then your storehouses will be completely filled, And your vats* will overflow with new wine. 11 My son, do not reject the discipline of Jehovah, And do not loathe his reproof, 12 For those whom Jehovah loves he reproves, Just as a father does a son in whom he delights. 13 Happy is the man who finds wisdom And the man who acquires discernment; 14 To gain it is better than gaining silver, And having it as profit is better than having gold. 15 It is more precious than corals;* Nothing you desire can compare to it. 16 Long life is in its right hand; Riches and glory are in its left hand. 17 Its ways are pleasant, And all its paths are peaceful. 18 It is a tree of life to those who take hold of it, And those who keep firm hold of it will be called happy. 19 Jehovah founded the earth in wisdom. He solidly established the heavens in discernment. 20 By his knowledge the watery deeps were split apart And the cloudy skies dripped with dew. 21 My son, do not lose sight of them.* Safeguard practical wisdom and thinking ability; 22 They will give you* life And be an adornment for your neck; 23 Then you will walk on your way in safety, And your foot will never stumble.* 24 When you lie down, you will have no fear; You will lie down, and your sleep will be pleasant. 25 You will not fear any sudden terror Nor the storm that is coming on the wicked. 26 For Jehovah will prove to be your source of confidence; He will keep your foot from being caught. 27 Do not withhold good from those to whom you should give it* If it is within your power* to help. 28 Do not say to your neighbor, “Go away; come back later! I will give it to you tomorrow,” If you can give it now. 29 Do not plot harm against your neighbor When he lives in a sense of security with you. 30 Do not quarrel with a man for no reason If he has done nothing bad to you. 31 Do not envy the violent man Nor choose any of his ways, 32 For Jehovah detests a devious person, But His close friendship is with the upright. 33 The curse of Jehovah is on the house of the wicked one, But he blesses the home of the righteous. 34 For he mocks those who ridicule, But he shows favor to the meek. 35 The wise will inherit honor, But the stupid ones glorify dishonor.

4 Listen, my sons, to the discipline of a father; Pay attention in order to gain understanding,  2 For I will give you good instruction; Do not forsake my teaching.*  3 I was a true son to my father And the one especially loved by my mother.  4 He taught me and said: “May your heart hold fast to my words. Keep my commandments and continue living.  5 Acquire wisdom, acquire understanding. Do not forget, and do not turn aside from what I say.  6 Do not forsake it, and it will protect you. Love it, and it will safeguard you.  7 Wisdom is the most important* thing, so acquire wisdom, And with all you acquire, acquire understanding.  8 Highly esteem it, and it will exalt you. It will honor you because you embrace it.  9 It will place an attractive wreath on your head; It will adorn you with a crown of beauty.” 10 Listen, my son, and accept my sayings, And the years of your life will be many. 11 I will instruct you in the way of wisdom; I will lead you in the tracks of uprightness. 12 When you walk, your steps will not be hindered; And if you run, you will not stumble. 13 Hold on to discipline; do not let it go. Safeguard it, for it means your life. 14 Do not enter the path of the wicked, And do not walk in the way of evil men. 15 Shun it, do not take it; Turn away from it, and pass it by. 16 For they cannot sleep unless they do what is bad. They are robbed of sleep unless they cause someone’s downfall. 17 They feed themselves with the bread of wickedness, And they drink the wine of violence. 18 But the path of the righteous is like the bright morning light That grows brighter and brighter until full daylight. 19 The way of the wicked is like the darkness; They do not know what makes them stumble. 20 My son, pay attention to my words; Listen carefully* to my sayings. 21 Do not lose sight of them; Keep them deep within your heart, 22 For they are life to those who find them And health to their whole body.* 23 Above all the things that you guard, safeguard your heart, For out of it are the sources of life. 24 Put crooked speech away from you, And keep devious talk far away from you. 25 Your eyes should look straight ahead, Yes, fix your gaze* straight ahead of you. 26 Smooth out* the course of your feet, And all your ways will be sure. 27 Do not incline to the right or the left. Turn your feet away from what is bad.

5 My son, pay attention to my wisdom. Listen carefully* to my discernment,  2 So that you may guard your thinking abilities And safeguard knowledge with your lips.  3 For the lips of a wayward* woman drip like a honeycomb, And her mouth is smoother than oil.  4 But in the end she is as bitter as wormwood And as sharp as a two-edged sword.  5 Her feet descend into death. Her steps lead straight to the Grave.*  6 She gives no thought to the path of life. Her course wanders, but she does not know where.  7 Now, my sons, listen to me And do not turn away from what I am saying.  8 Stay far away from her; Do not go near the entrance of her house,  9 So that you may not give your dignity to others Nor reap years of what is cruel; 10 So that strangers may not drain your resources* And what you labored for go to the house of a foreigner. 11 Otherwise, you will groan at the end of your life When your flesh and body waste away 12 And you say: “How I hated discipline! How my heart despised reproof! 13 I did not listen to the voice of my instructors Or pay attention to my teachers. 14 I have come to the brink of complete ruin In the midst of the entire congregation.”* 15 Drink water from your own cistern And flowing* water from your own well. 16 Should your springs be dispersed outside, Your streams of water in the public squares? 17 Let them be for you alone, And not for strangers with you. 18 May your own fountain* be blessed, And may you rejoice with the wife of your youth, 19 A loving doe, a graceful mountain goat.* Let her breasts satisfy* you at all times. May you be captivated by her love constantly. 20 So why, my son, should you be captivated by a wayward* woman Or embrace the bosom of an immoral* woman? 21 For the ways of man are before the eyes of Jehovah; He examines all his paths. 22 The wicked one is ensnared by his own errors, And he will be caught in the ropes of his own sin. 23 He will die for lack of discipline And go astray because of his excessive foolishness.

6 My son, if you have put up security* for your neighbor, If you have given your handshake* to a stranger,  2 If you have been ensnared by your promise, Caught by the words of your mouth,  3 Do this, my son, and free yourself, For you have fallen into the hand of your neighbor: Go and humble yourself and urgently plead with your neighbor.  4 Do not allow your eyes to sleep, Nor your eyelids to slumber.  5 Free yourself like a gazelle from the hunter’s hand, Like a bird from the hand of the birdcatcher.  6 Go to the ant, you lazy one; Observe its ways and become wise.  7 Although it has no commander, officer, or ruler,  8 It prepares its food in the summer, And it gathers its food supplies in the harvest.  9 How long, you lazy one, will you lie there? When will you rise up from your sleep? 10 A little sleep, a little slumbering, A little folding of the hands to rest, 11 And your poverty will come like a bandit, And your want like an armed man. 12 A useless and wicked man walks about with crooked speech; 13 He winks with his eye, signals with his foot, and motions with his fingers. 14 With a perverted heart, He is always scheming evil and spreading contentions. 15 Therefore, his disaster will come suddenly; In a moment he will be broken beyond healing. 16 There are six things that Jehovah hates; Yes, seven things that he* detests: 17 Haughty eyes, a lying tongue, and hands that shed innocent blood, 18 A heart plotting wicked schemes, and feet that run quickly to evil, 19 A false witness who lies with every breath, And anyone sowing contentions among brothers. 20 Observe, my son, the commandment of your father, And do not forsake the instruction* of your mother. 21 Always bind them around your heart; Tie them about your neck. 22 When you walk about, it will lead you; When you lie down, it will stand guard over you; And when you awaken, it will speak to you.* 23 For the commandment is a lamp, And the law is a light, And the reproofs of discipline are the way to life. 24 They will guard you against the bad woman, Against the seductive tongue of the immoral* woman. 25 Do not desire her beauty in your heart Or allow her to captivate you with her alluring eyes, 26 For because of a prostitute, a man is reduced to a loaf of bread, But the wife of another man preys on a precious life.* 27 Can a man rake fire to his chest and not burn his garments? 28 Or can a man walk on hot coals without scorching his feet? 29 It is the same with anyone having relations with his neighbor’s wife; No one who touches her will go unpunished. 30 People do not despise a thief If he steals to satisfy himself* when he is hungry. 31 Yet, when found, he will repay sevenfold; He will give up all the valuables of his house. 32 Anyone committing adultery with a woman is lacking good sense;* The one who does so brings ruin on himself.* 33 He will get only wounds and dishonor, And his disgrace will not be wiped away. 34 For jealousy makes a husband furious; He will show no compassion when he takes revenge. 35 He will accept no compensation;* He will not be appeased, no matter how large you make the gift.

Lit., “To know.”

Or “what is just.”

Or “fairness.”

Or “wise guidance.”

Or “a parable.”

Or “reverence for.”

Or “law.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “Throw in your lot with us.”

Or “share a common bag (purse).”

Or “souls.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “head.”

Or “Turn back when I reprove.”

Lit., “eat from the fruit.”

Or “schemes; plans.”

See Glossary.

Lit., “strange.” Evidently, one morally estranged from God.

Or “seductive.”

Lit., “foreign.” Evidently, one morally alienated from God.

Or “the husband.”

Lit., “tracks.”

Lit., “going in to.”

Or “the one who keeps integrity.”

Or “law.”

Or “truth.”

Lit., “lean.”

Lit., “navel.”

Or “very best.”

Or “income.”

Or “winepresses.”

See Glossary.

Evidently referring to God’s qualities mentioned in the previous verses.

Or “your soul.”

Or “strike against anything.”

Or “to whom it is owing.”

Or “within the power of your hand.”

Or “law.”

Or “the prime.”

Lit., “Incline your ear.”

Lit., “to all their flesh.”

Or “beaming eyes.”

Or possibly, “Carefully consider.”

Lit., “Incline your ear.”

Lit., “strange.” See Pr 2:16.

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “power.”

Lit., “In the midst of the assembly and the congregation.”

Or “fresh.”

Or “water source.”

Or “ibex.”

Or “intoxicate.”

Lit., “strange.” See Pr 2:16.

Lit., “foreign.” See Pr 2:16.

Lit., “gone surety.”

That is, in a pledge.

Or “his soul.”

Or “law.”

Or “instruct you.”

Lit., “foreign.” See Pr 2:16.

Or “soul.”

Or “fill his soul.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “ransom.”

^ (Prov. 3:1-35) My son, do not forget my teaching,* And may your heart observe my commandments,  2 Because they will add many days And years of life and peace to you.  3 Do not let loyal love and faithfulness* leave you. Tie them around your neck; Write them on the tablet of your heart;  4 Then you will find favor and good insight In the eyes of God and man.  5 Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, And do not rely* on your own understanding.  6 In all your ways take notice of him, And he will make your paths straight.  7 Do not become wise in your own eyes. Fear Jehovah and turn away from bad.  8 It will be a healing to your body* And refreshment for your bones.  9 Honor Jehovah with your valuable things, With the firstfruits* of all your produce;* 10 Then your storehouses will be completely filled, And your vats* will overflow with new wine. 11 My son, do not reject the discipline of Jehovah, And do not loathe his reproof, 12 For those whom Jehovah loves he reproves, Just as a father does a son in whom he delights. 13 Happy is the man who finds wisdom And the man who acquires discernment; 14 To gain it is better than gaining silver, And having it as profit is better than having gold. 15 It is more precious than corals;* Nothing you desire can compare to it. 16 Long life is in its right hand; Riches and glory are in its left hand. 17 Its ways are pleasant, And all its paths are peaceful. 18 It is a tree of life to those who take hold of it, And those who keep firm hold of it will be called happy. 19 Jehovah founded the earth in wisdom. He solidly established the heavens in discernment. 20 By his knowledge the watery deeps were split apart And the cloudy skies dripped with dew. 21 My son, do not lose sight of them.* Safeguard practical wisdom and thinking ability; 22 They will give you* life And be an adornment for your neck; 23 Then you will walk on your way in safety, And your foot will never stumble.* 24 When you lie down, you will have no fear; You will lie down, and your sleep will be pleasant. 25 You will not fear any sudden terror Nor the storm that is coming on the wicked. 26 For Jehovah will prove to be your source of confidence; He will keep your foot from being caught. 27 Do not withhold good from those to whom you should give it* If it is within your power* to help. 28 Do not say to your neighbor, “Go away; come back later! I will give it to you tomorrow,” If you can give it now. 29 Do not plot harm against your neighbor When he lives in a sense of security with you. 30 Do not quarrel with a man for no reason If he has done nothing bad to you. 31 Do not envy the violent man Nor choose any of his ways, 32 For Jehovah detests a devious person, But His close friendship is with the upright. 33 The curse of Jehovah is on the house of the wicked one, But he blesses the home of the righteous. 34 For he mocks those who ridicule, But he shows favor to the meek. 35 The wise will inherit honor, But the stupid ones glorify dishonor.

Or “law.”

Or “truth.”

Lit., “lean.”

Lit., “navel.”

Or “very best.”

Or “income.”

Or “winepresses.”

See Glossary.

Evidently referring to God’s qualities mentioned in the previous verses.

Or “your soul.”

Or “strike against anything.”

Or “to whom it is owing.”

Or “within the power of your hand.”

^ (Prov. 7:1-11:31) My son, keep my sayings, And treasure up my commandments.  2 Keep my commandments and live; Guard my instruction* like the pupil of your eye.  3 Tie them around your fingers; Write them on the tablet of your heart.  4 Say to wisdom, “You are my sister,” And call understanding “my relative,”  5 To guard you against the wayward* woman, Against the immoral* woman and her smooth* words.  6 From the window of my house, Through my lattice, I looked down,  7 And as I observed the naive* ones, I discerned among the youths a young man lacking good sense.*  8 He passed along the street near her corner, And he marched in the direction of her house  9 In the twilight, in the evening, At the approach of night and darkness. 10 Then I saw a woman meet him, Dressed like* a prostitute, with a cunning heart. 11 She is loud and defiant. She never stays* at home. 12 One moment she is outside, next she is in the public squares, She lurks near every corner. 13 She grabs hold of him and gives him a kiss; With a bold face, she says to him: 14 “I had to offer communion sacrifices. Today I paid my vows. 15 That is why I came out to meet you, To look for you, and I found you! 16 I have spread fine covers upon my bed, Colorful linen from Egypt. 17 I have sprinkled my bed with myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon. 18 Come, let us drink our fill of love until the morning; Let us enjoy passionate love together, 19 For my husband is not at home; He has gone on a distant journey. 20 He took a bag of money with him, And he will not return until the day of the full moon.” 21 She misleads him with great persuasiveness. She seduces him with smooth speech. 22 Suddenly he goes after her, like a bull to the slaughter, Like a fool to be punished in the stocks,* 23 Until an arrow pierces his liver; Like a bird rushing into a trap, he does not know that it will cost him his life.* 24 And now, my sons, listen to me; Pay attention to the words I speak. 25 Do not let your heart turn aside to her ways. Do not stray onto her paths, 26 For she has caused many to fall down slain, And those she has killed are numerous. 27 Her house leads to the Grave;* It goes down to the inner chambers of death.

8 Is not wisdom calling out? Is not discernment raising its voice?  2 On the heights along the road, It takes its position at the crossroads.  3 Next to the gates leading into the city, At the entrances of the doorways, It keeps crying out loudly:  4 “To you, O people, I am calling; I raise my voice to everyone.*  5 You inexperienced ones, learn shrewdness; You stupid ones, acquire an understanding heart.*  6 Listen, for what I say is important, My lips speak what is right;  7 For my mouth softly utters truth, And my lips detest what is wicked.  8 All the sayings of my mouth are righteous. None of them are twisted or crooked.  9 They are all straightforward to the discerning And right to those who have found knowledge. 10 Take my discipline instead of silver, And knowledge rather than the finest gold, 11 For wisdom is better than corals;* All other desirable things cannot compare to it. 12 I, wisdom, dwell together with shrewdness; I have found knowledge and thinking ability. 13 The fear of Jehovah means the hating of bad. I hate self-exaltation and pride and the evil way and perverse speech. 14 I possess good advice and practical wisdom; Understanding and power are mine. 15 By me kings keep reigning, And high officials decree righteousness. 16 By me princes keep ruling, And nobles judge in righteousness. 17 I love those loving me, And those seeking me will find me. 18 Riches and glory are with me, Lasting wealth* and righteousness. 19 My fruitage is better than gold, even refined gold, And what I produce is better than the finest silver. 20 I walk in the path of righteousness, In the middle of the pathways of justice; 21 I give a rich inheritance to those who love me, And I fill up their storehouses. 22 Jehovah produced me as the beginning of his way, The earliest of his achievements of long ago. 23 From ancient times* I was installed, From the start, from times earlier than the earth. 24 When there were no deep waters, I was brought forth,* When there were no springs overflowing with water. 25 Before the mountains were set in place, Before the hills, I was brought forth, 26 When he had not yet made the earth and its fields Or the first clods of earth’s soil. 27 When he prepared the heavens, I was there; When he marked out the horizon* on the surface of the waters, 28 When he established* the clouds above, When he founded the fountains of the deep, 29 When he set a decree for the sea That its waters should not pass beyond his order, When he established* the foundations of the earth, 30 Then I was beside him as a master worker. I was the one he was especially fond of day by day; I rejoiced before him all the time; 31 I rejoiced over his habitable earth, And I was especially fond of the sons of men.* 32 And now, my sons, listen to me; Yes, happy are those who keep my ways. 33 Listen to discipline and become wise, And never neglect it. 34 Happy is the man who listens to me By coming early to* my doors day by day, By waiting next to my doorposts; 35 For the one finding me will find life, And he receives approval from Jehovah. 36 But the one who ignores me harms himself,* And those who hate me love death.”

9 True wisdom has built its house; It has carved* out its seven pillars.  2 It has fully prepared its meat;* It has mixed its wine; It has also arranged its table.  3 It has sent out its female servants To call out from the heights above the city:  4 “Whoever is inexperienced, let him come in here.” She says to the one lacking good sense:*  5 “Come, eat my bread And share in drinking the wine that I have mixed.  6 Leave behind your inexperience* and live; Walk forward in the way of understanding.”  7 The one who corrects a ridiculer invites dishonor, And whoever reproves someone wicked will get hurt.  8 Do not reprove a ridiculer, or he will hate you. Reprove a wise person, and he will love you.  9 Share with a wise person, and he will become wiser. Teach someone righteous, and he will add to his learning. 10 The fear of Jehovah is the beginning of wisdom, And knowledge of the Most Holy One is understanding. 11 For by me your days will be many, And years will be added to your life. 12 If you become wise, you are wise to your own advantage, But if you are a ridiculer, you alone will bear it. 13 A stupid woman is loud. She is ignorant and knows absolutely nothing. 14 She sits at the entrance of her house On a seat in the high places of the city, 15 Calling out to those passing by, To those walking straight ahead on their way: 16 “Whoever is inexperienced, let him come in here.” She says to those lacking good sense:* 17 “Stolen waters are sweet, And food eaten in secret is pleasant.” 18 But he does not know that those powerless in death are there, That her guests are in the depths of the Grave.*

10 Proverbs of Solʹo·mon. A wise son makes his father rejoice, But a foolish son is the grief of his mother.  2 The treasures gained by wickedness will be of no benefit, But righteousness is what rescues from death.  3 Jehovah will not cause the righteous one* to go hungry, But he will deny the wicked what they crave.  4 Idle hands will cause poverty, But diligent hands bring riches.  5 The son acting with insight gathers the crop in summer, But the son acting shamefully is fast asleep during the harvest.  6 Blessings are on the head of the righteous one, But the mouth of the wicked conceals violence.  7 The memory* of the righteous one is due for a blessing, But the name of the wicked will rot.  8 The wisehearted person will accept instructions,* But the one speaking foolishly will be trodden down.  9 The one walking in integrity will walk in security, But the one making his ways crooked will be found out. 10 The one who slyly winks his eye causes grief, And the one who speaks foolishly will be trodden down. 11 The mouth of the righteous one is a source of life, But the mouth of the wicked conceals violence. 12 Hatred is what stirs up contentions, But love covers over all transgressions. 13 Wisdom is found on the lips of the discerning person, But the rod is for the back of one lacking good sense.* 14 Those who are wise treasure up knowledge, But the mouth of the fool invites ruin. 15 The wealth* of a rich man is his fortified city. The ruin of the poor is their poverty. 16 The activity of the righteous one leads to life; But the produce of the wicked one leads to sin. 17 The one who heeds discipline is a path to life,* But the one who ignores reproof leads others astray. 18 The one who conceals his hatred speaks lies, And the one spreading malicious reports* is stupid. 19 When words are many, transgression cannot be avoided, But whoever controls his lips acts discreetly. 20 The tongue of the righteous one is like the finest silver, But the heart of the wicked one is worth little. 21 The lips of the righteous one nourish* many, But the foolish die for lack of sense. 22 It is the blessing of Jehovah that makes one rich, And He adds no pain* with it. 23 Engaging in shameful conduct is like a game to the stupid one, But wisdom is for the man of discernment. 24 What the wicked one fears will come upon him; But the desire of the righteous will be granted. 25 When the storm passes by, the wicked one will be no more, But the righteous one is a foundation forever. 26 Like vinegar to the teeth and smoke to the eyes, So the lazy person is to the one who sends him.* 27 The fear of Jehovah prolongs life, But the years of the wicked will be cut short. 28 The expectation* of the righteous brings joy, But the hope of the wicked will perish. 29 The way of Jehovah is a stronghold for the blameless one, But it means ruin for evildoers. 30 The righteous one will never be made to fall, But the wicked will no longer inhabit the earth. 31 The mouth of the righteous one produces* wisdom, But the perverse tongue will be cut off. 32 The lips of the righteous one know what is pleasing, But the mouth of the wicked is perverse.

11 Dishonest* scales are detestable to Jehovah, But an accurate weight* brings pleasure to him.  2 When presumptuousness comes, dishonor will follow, But wisdom is with the modest ones.  3 The integrity of the upright is what guides them, But the deviousness of the treacherous will destroy them.  4 Wealth* will be of no benefit on the day of fury, But righteousness is what will rescue from death.  5 The righteousness of the blameless one makes his path straight, But the wicked one will fall because of his own wickedness.  6 The righteousness of the upright will rescue them, But the treacherous will be caught by their own desires.  7 When a wicked man dies, his hope perishes; And expectations based on his power also perish.  8 The righteous one is rescued from distress, And the wicked one takes his place.  9 By his mouth the apostate* brings his neighbor to ruin, But by knowledge the righteous are rescued. 10 The goodness of the righteous makes a city rejoice, And when the wicked perish, there is a joyful cry. 11 Because of the blessing of the upright a city is exalted, But the mouth of the wicked tears it down. 12 Whoever is lacking good sense* shows contempt for* his neighbor, But the man of true discernment remains silent. 13 A slanderer goes about revealing confidential talk, But the trustworthy person* keeps a confidence.* 14 When there is no skillful direction,* the people fall, But there is success* through many advisers.* 15 Whoever guarantees a loan* for a stranger is sure to fare badly, But whoever avoids* shaking hands in a pledge will be secure. 16 A gracious* woman acquires glory, But ruthless men seize riches. 17 A kind man* benefits himself,* But the cruel person brings trouble* on himself. 18 The wicked one earns deceptive wages, But the one who sows righteousness receives a true reward. 19 The one standing firmly for righteousness is in line for life, But the one chasing after evil is in line for death. 20 Those crooked at heart are detestable to Jehovah, But those whose way is blameless bring pleasure to him. 21 Be assured of this:* An evil person will not go unpunished, But the children of the righteous will escape. 22 Like a gold ring in the snout of a pig Is a beautiful woman who rejects good sense. 23 The desire of the righteous leads to good, But what the wicked hope for leads to fury. 24 One gives generously* and ends up with more; Another withholds what should be given, but he comes to poverty. 25 The generous person* will prosper,* And whoever refreshes* others will himself be refreshed. 26 The people will curse the one who withholds grain, But they will bless the one who sells it. 27 The one who diligently seeks to do good seeks favor, But the one searching for bad—that is what will surely come upon him. 28 The one trusting in his riches will fall, But the righteous will flourish like the foliage. 29 Anyone who brings trouble* on his household will inherit the wind, And the fool will be a servant to the wisehearted one. 30 The fruitage of the righteous one is a tree of life, And the one who wins souls* is wise. 31 If, indeed, the righteous one on earth is rewarded, How much more the wicked one and the sinner!

Or “law.”

Lit., “strange.” See Pr 2:16.

Lit., “foreign.” See Pr 2:16.

Or “seductive.”

Or “inexperienced.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “with the garment of.”

Lit., “Her feet never stay.”

Or “fetters.”

Or “soul.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Lit., “to the sons of men.”

Lit., “understand heart.”

See Glossary.

Or “Hereditary values.”

Or “From time immemorial.”

Or “brought forth as with labor pains.”

Lit., “a circle.”

Lit., “made strong.”

Or “decreed.”

Or “mankind.”

Or “By keeping awake at.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “hewed.”

Lit., “She has slaughtered her slaughtering.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “the inexperienced ones.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “the soul of the righteous one.”

Or “reputation.”

Lit., “commandments.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “valuable thing.”

Or possibly, “is on the path to life.”

Or “rumors.”

Or “guide.”

Or “sorrow; hardship.”

Or “to his employer.”

Or “hope.”

Or “bears the fruit of.”

Or “Cheating.”

Or “a complete stone weight.”

Or “Valuable things.”

Or “godless man.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “despises.”

Lit., “the one faithful in spirit.”

Lit., “covers over a matter.”

Or “wise guidance.”

Or “salvation.”

Or “counselors.”

Or “puts up security.”

Lit., “hates.”

Or “charming.”

Or “A man of loyal love.”

Or “does good to his soul.”

Or “disgrace.”

Lit., “Hand to hand.”

Lit., “scatters.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “will be made fat.”

Lit., “freely waters.”

Or “disgrace.”

See Glossary.

^ (Prov. 7:13-23) She grabs hold of him and gives him a kiss; With a bold face, she says to him: 14 “I had to offer communion sacrifices. Today I paid my vows. 15 That is why I came out to meet you, To look for you, and I found you! 16 I have spread fine covers upon my bed, Colorful linen from Egypt. 17 I have sprinkled my bed with myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon. 18 Come, let us drink our fill of love until the morning; Let us enjoy passionate love together, 19 For my husband is not at home; He has gone on a distant journey. 20 He took a bag of money with him, And he will not return until the day of the full moon.” 21 She misleads him with great persuasiveness. She seduces him with smooth speech. 22 Suddenly he goes after her, like a bull to the slaughter, Like a fool to be punished in the stocks,* 23 Until an arrow pierces his liver; Like a bird rushing into a trap, he does not know that it will cost him his life.*

Or “fetters.”

Or “soul.”

^ (Prov. 8:22-9:6) Jehovah produced me as the beginning of his way, The earliest of his achievements of long ago. 23 From ancient times* I was installed, From the start, from times earlier than the earth. 24 When there were no deep waters, I was brought forth,* When there were no springs overflowing with water. 25 Before the mountains were set in place, Before the hills, I was brought forth, 26 When he had not yet made the earth and its fields Or the first clods of earth’s soil. 27 When he prepared the heavens, I was there; When he marked out the horizon* on the surface of the waters, 28 When he established* the clouds above, When he founded the fountains of the deep, 29 When he set a decree for the sea That its waters should not pass beyond his order, When he established* the foundations of the earth, 30 Then I was beside him as a master worker. I was the one he was especially fond of day by day; I rejoiced before him all the time; 31 I rejoiced over his habitable earth, And I was especially fond of the sons of men.* 32 And now, my sons, listen to me; Yes, happy are those who keep my ways. 33 Listen to discipline and become wise, And never neglect it. 34 Happy is the man who listens to me By coming early to* my doors day by day, By waiting next to my doorposts; 35 For the one finding me will find life, And he receives approval from Jehovah. 36 But the one who ignores me harms himself,* And those who hate me love death.”

9 True wisdom has built its house; It has carved* out its seven pillars.  2 It has fully prepared its meat;* It has mixed its wine; It has also arranged its table.  3 It has sent out its female servants To call out from the heights above the city:  4 “Whoever is inexperienced, let him come in here.” She says to the one lacking good sense:*  5 “Come, eat my bread And share in drinking the wine that I have mixed.  6 Leave behind your inexperience* and live; Walk forward in the way of understanding.”

Or “From time immemorial.”

Or “brought forth as with labor pains.”

Lit., “a circle.”

Lit., “made strong.”

Or “decreed.”

Or “mankind.”

Or “By keeping awake at.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “hewed.”

Lit., “She has slaughtered her slaughtering.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “the inexperienced ones.”

^ ***sn song 32 Be Steadfast, Unmovable!***

Song 32

Be Steadfast, Unmovable!

(1 Corinthians 15:58)

1. Nations are troubled as never before.

People are fearful of what lies in store.

Firm and unmovable we need to be,

Serving our God faithfully.

(CHORUS)

Steadfast we all need to be;

Far from this world we keep free,

As we feed on God’s truth and keep integrity.

2. Snares of this world and temptations abound.

We can resist if our thinking is sound.

If we hold fast to what God says is true,

Safely he’ll carry us through.

(CHORUS)

Steadfast we all need to be;

Far from this world we keep free,

As we feed on God’s truth and keep integrity.

3. Give to God worship that comes from the heart.

In the Lord’s service may we have a part.

Preach the good news, always holding it fast.

Soon the last days will have passed.

(CHORUS)

Steadfast we all need to be;

Far from this world we keep free,

As we feed on God’s truth and keep integrity.

(See also [Luke 21:9;][1 Pet. 4:7].)

^ (1 Cor. 15:58) Therefore, my beloved brothers, be steadfast, immovable, always having plenty to do in the work of the Lord, knowing that your labor is not in vain in connection with the Lord.

^ (Luke 21:9) Furthermore, when you hear of wars and disturbances,* do not be terrified. For these things must take place first, but the end will not occur immediately.”

Or “disorders; uprisings.”

^ (1 Pet. 4:7) But the end of all things has drawn close. Therefore, be sound in mind, and be vigilant* with a view to prayers.

Or “alert; awake.”

^ ***w00 11/15 pp. 29-30 “Keep My Commandments and Continue Living”***

a need to treat such instructions “like the pupil of your eyes”—guarding them with utmost care. That is the way to avoid the deadly effect of ignoring Jehovah’s standards and thus to “continue living.”

“Tie them [my commandments] upon your fingers,” continues Solomon, “and write them upon the tablet of your heart.” ([Proverbs 7:3]) As fingers are prominently before our eyes and are vital in carrying out our purposes, the lessons learned from a Scriptural upbringing or the gaining of Bible knowledge are to be a constant reminder and guide in everything we do. We are to inscribe them upon the tablet of our heart, making them a part of our nature.

Not forgetting the importance of wisdom and understanding, the king exhorts: “Say to wisdom: ‘You are my sister’; and may you call understanding itself ‘Kinswoman.’” ([Proverbs 7:4]) Wisdom is the ability to put God-given knowledge to proper use. We should have affection for wisdom as for a dearly loved sister. What is understanding? It is the ability to see into a matter and get the sense of it by grasping the connections between its parts and the whole. Understanding must be as close to us as an intimate friend.

Why should we adhere to Scriptural training and cultivate closeness with wisdom and understanding? So as “to guard [ourselves] against the woman stranger, against the foreigner who has made her own sayings smooth.” ([Proverbs 7:5]) Yes, doing so will protect us from the smooth and persuasive ways of a stranger, or foreigner—an immoral person.*

The Young Man Meets ‘a Cunning Woman’

The king of Israel next describes a scene that he himself has observed: “At the window of my house, through my lattice I looked down, that I might peer upon the inexperienced ones. I was interested in discerning among the sons a young man in want of heart, passing along on the street near her corner, and in the way to her house he marches, in the twilight, in the evening of the day, at the approach of the night and the gloom.”—Proverbs 7:6-9.

The window through which Solomon looks out has a lattice—apparently a framework with laths and perhaps elaborate carvings. As the twilight fades, the darkness of the night pours into the streets. He catches sight of a young man who is particularly vulnerable. Lacking discernment, or good sense, he is in want of heart. Likely, he is aware of the type of neighborhood he has entered and what could happen to him there. The young man comes near “her corner,” which is on the way to her house. Who is she? What is she up to?

The observant king continues: “Look! there was a woman to meet him, with the garment of a prostitute and cunning of heart. She is boisterous and stubborn. In her house her feet do not keep residing. Now she is outdoors, now she is in the public squares, and near every corner she lies in wait.”—Proverbs 7:10-12.

This woman’s manner of dress speaks volumes about her. (Genesis 38:14, 15) She is dressed immodestly, like a prostitute. Moreover, she is cunning of heart—her mind is “treacherous,” her intent “crafty.” (An American Translation; New International Version) She is boisterous and stubborn, talkative and headstrong, loud and self-willed, brazen and defiant. Rather than staying at home, she prefers to frequent public places, lurking on street corners to pick up her prey. She is waiting for someone like the young man.

An ‘Abundance of Persuasiveness’

A young man thus meets a loose woman with a crafty plan. How this must have caught the attention of Solomon! He relates: “She has grabbed hold of him and given him a kiss. She has put on a bold face, and she begins to say to him: ‘Communion sacrifices were incumbent upon me. Today I have paid my vows. That is why I have come out to meet you, to look for your face, that I may find you.’”—Proverbs 7:13-15.

The lips of this woman are smooth. Putting on a bold face, she utters her words confidently. Everything she says is carefully calculated to seduce the young man. By stating that she had made communion sacrifices that very day and paid her vows, she makes a display of righteousness, hinting that she is not lacking in spirituality. Communion sacrifices at the temple in Jerusalem consisted of meat, flour, oil, and wine. (Leviticus 19:5, 6;[22:21;] Numbers 15:8-10) Since the offerer could take part of the communion sacrifice for himself and his family, she thus suggests that there is plenty to eat and drink at her house. The implication is clear: The young man would have a good time there. She has come out of her house specifically to look for him. How touching—if anyone could swallow such a story. “It is true she was out looking for someone,” says one Bible scholar, “but did she really come looking just for this one special fellow? Only a fool—perhaps this one—would believe her.”

After making herself appealing by the sight of her attire, by the sound of her flattering words, by the touch of her embrace, and by the taste of her lips, the seductress enlists the sense of smell. She says: “With coverlets I have bedecked my divan, with many-colored things, linen of Egypt. I have besprinkled my bed with myrrh, aloes and cinnamon.” (Proverbs 7:16, 17) She has aesthetically prepared her bed with colorful linen from Egypt and perfumed it with choice fragrances of myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon.

“Do come, let us drink our fill of love until the morning,” she continues, “do let us enjoy each other with love expressions.” The invitation is to something much more than a pleasant dinner for two. Her promise is that of enjoying sexual intimacy. To the young man, the appeal is adventurous and exciting! As further inducement, she adds: “For the husband is not in his house; he has gone traveling on a way of some distance. A bag of money he has taken in his hand. On the day of the full moon he will come to his house.” (Proverbs 7:18-20) They would be perfectly safe, she assures him, for her husband is away on a business trip and is not expected back for some time. How talented she is at beguiling a young person! “She has misled him by the abundance of her persuasiveness. By the smoothness of her lips she seduces him.” (Proverbs 7:21) It would take a man of Joseph’s caliber to resist an appeal

^ (Prov. 7:3) Tie them around your fingers; Write them on the tablet of your heart.

^ (Prov. 7:4) Say to wisdom, “You are my sister,” And call understanding “my relative,”

^ (Prov. 7:5) To guard you against the wayward* woman, Against the immoral* woman and her smooth* words.

Lit., “strange.” See Pr 2:16.

Lit., “foreign.” See Pr 2:16.

Or “seductive.”

^ (Prov. 7:6-9) From the window of my house, Through my lattice, I looked down,  7 And as I observed the naive* ones, I discerned among the youths a young man lacking good sense.*  8 He passed along the street near her corner, And he marched in the direction of her house  9 In the twilight, in the evening, At the approach of night and darkness.

Or “inexperienced.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

^ (Prov. 7:10-12) Then I saw a woman meet him, Dressed like* a prostitute, with a cunning heart. 11 She is loud and defiant. She never stays* at home. 12 One moment she is outside, next she is in the public squares, She lurks near every corner.

Or “with the garment of.”

Lit., “Her feet never stay.”

^ (Gen. 38:14, 15) With that she removed her widow’s clothing and veiled herself and covered herself with a shawl and sat down at the entrance of E·naʹim, which is on the road to Timʹnah, for she saw that Sheʹlah had grown up and yet she had not been given to him as a wife. 15 When Judah caught sight of her, he at once took her for a prostitute, because she had covered her face.

^ (Prov. 7:13-15) She grabs hold of him and gives him a kiss; With a bold face, she says to him: 14 “I had to offer communion sacrifices. Today I paid my vows. 15 That is why I came out to meet you, To look for you, and I found you!

^ (Lev. 19:5, 6) “‘Now if you offer a communion sacrifice to Jehovah, you should sacrifice it in such a way that you gain approval for yourselves. 6 It should be eaten on the day of your sacrifice and on the next day, but what is left over until the third day should be burned in the fire.

^ (Lev. 22:21) “‘If a man presents a communion sacrifice to Jehovah to pay a vow or as a voluntary offering, it should be a sound animal from the herd or the flock, in order to gain approval. No defect at all should be in it.

^ (Num. 15:8-10) “‘But if you should offer a male of the herd as a burnt offering or a sacrifice to perform a special vow or communion sacrifices to Jehovah, 9 you should also present together with the male of the herd a grain offering of three tenths of an eʹphah measure of fine flour mixed with half a hin of oil. 10 You should also present wine as a drink offering, half a hin, as an offering made by fire, as a pleasing* aroma to Jehovah.

Or “appeasing; soothing.” Lit., “restful.”

^ (Prov. 7:16, 17) I have spread fine covers upon my bed, Colorful linen from Egypt. 17 I have sprinkled my bed with myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon.

^ (Prov. 7:18-20) Come, let us drink our fill of love until the morning; Let us enjoy passionate love together, 19 For my husband is not at home; He has gone on a distant journey. 20 He took a bag of money with him, And he will not return until the day of the full moon.”

^ (Prov. 7:21) She misleads him with great persuasiveness. She seduces him with smooth speech.

^ par. 11 The word “stranger” was applied to those who alienated themselves from Jehovah by turning away from the Law. Thus, an immoral female, such as a prostitute, is referred to as a “woman stranger.”

^ ***w00 11/15 pp. 30-31 “Keep My Commandments and Continue Living”***

what could happen to him there. The young man comes near “her corner,” which is on the way to her house. Who is she? What is she up to?

The observant king continues: “Look! there was a woman to meet him, with the garment of a prostitute and cunning of heart. She is boisterous and stubborn. In her house her feet do not keep residing. Now she is outdoors, now she is in the public squares, and near every corner she lies in wait.”—Proverbs 7:10-12.

This woman’s manner of dress speaks volumes about her. (Genesis 38:14, 15) She is dressed immodestly, like a prostitute. Moreover, she is cunning of heart—her mind is “treacherous,” her intent “crafty.” (An American Translation; New International Version) She is boisterous and stubborn, talkative and headstrong, loud and self-willed, brazen and defiant. Rather than staying at home, she prefers to frequent public places, lurking on street corners to pick up her prey. She is waiting for someone like the young man.

An ‘Abundance of Persuasiveness’

A young man thus meets a loose woman with a crafty plan. How this must have caught the attention of Solomon! He relates: “She has grabbed hold of him and given him a kiss. She has put on a bold face, and she begins to say to him: ‘Communion sacrifices were incumbent upon me. Today I have paid my vows. That is why I have come out to meet you, to look for your face, that I may find you.’”—Proverbs 7:13-15.

The lips of this woman are smooth. Putting on a bold face, she utters her words confidently. Everything she says is carefully calculated to seduce the young man. By stating that she had made communion sacrifices that very day and paid her vows, she makes a display of righteousness, hinting that she is not lacking in spirituality. Communion sacrifices at the temple in Jerusalem consisted of meat, flour, oil, and wine. (Leviticus 19:5, 6;[22:21;] Numbers 15:8-10) Since the offerer could take part of the communion sacrifice for himself and his family, she thus suggests that there is plenty to eat and drink at her house. The implication is clear: The young man would have a good time there. She has come out of her house specifically to look for him. How touching—if anyone could swallow such a story. “It is true she was out looking for someone,” says one Bible scholar, “but did she really come looking just for this one special fellow? Only a fool—perhaps this one—would believe her.”

After making herself appealing by the sight of her attire, by the sound of her flattering words, by the touch of her embrace, and by the taste of her lips, the seductress enlists the sense of smell. She says: “With coverlets I have bedecked my divan, with many-colored things, linen of Egypt. I have besprinkled my bed with myrrh, aloes and cinnamon.” (Proverbs 7:16, 17) She has aesthetically prepared her bed with colorful linen from Egypt and perfumed it with choice fragrances of myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon.

“Do come, let us drink our fill of love until the morning,” she continues, “do let us enjoy each other with love expressions.” The invitation is to something much more than a pleasant dinner for two. Her promise is that of enjoying sexual intimacy. To the young man, the appeal is adventurous and exciting! As further inducement, she adds: “For the husband is not in his house; he has gone traveling on a way of some distance. A bag of money he has taken in his hand. On the day of the full moon he will come to his house.” (Proverbs 7:18-20) They would be perfectly safe, she assures him, for her husband is away on a business trip and is not expected back for some time. How talented she is at beguiling a young person! “She has misled him by the abundance of her persuasiveness. By the smoothness of her lips she seduces him.” (Proverbs 7:21) It would take a man of Joseph’s caliber to resist an appeal this enticing. (Genesis 39:9,[12]) Does this young man measure up?

‘Like a Bull to the Slaughter’

“All of a sudden he is going after her,” reports Solomon, “like a bull that comes even to the slaughter, and just as if fettered for the discipline of a foolish man, until an arrow cleaves open his liver, just as a bird hastens into the trap, and he has not known that it involves his very soul.”—Proverbs 7:22, 23.

The invitation proves to be irresistible to the young man. Throwing all good sense to the wind, he goes after her ‘like a bull to the slaughter.’ As a man in fetters cannot escape his punishment, so the young man is drawn into sin. He does not see the danger of it all until “an arrow cleaves open his liver,” that is, until he receives a wound that can cause his death. The death may be physical in that he exposes himself to death-dealing sexually transmitted diseases.* The wound can also cause his spiritual death; “it involves his very soul.” His entire being and his life are seriously affected, and he has gravely sinned against God. He thus hastens into the grip of death like a bird into a trap!

“Do Not Wander Into Her Roadways”

Drawing a lesson from what he has seen, the wise king urges: “And now, O sons, listen to me and pay attention to the sayings of my mouth. May your heart not turn aside to her ways. Do not wander into her roadways. For many are the ones she has caused to fall down slain, and all those being killed by her are numerous. The ways to Sheol her house is; they are descending to the interior rooms of death.”—Proverbs 7:24-27.

Clearly, the counsel of Solomon is to turn aside from the death-dealing ways of an immoral person and “continue living.” ([Proverbs 7:2]) How timely this advice is for our day! Surely there is a need to avoid places frequented by those who are lying in wait to pick up prey. Why should you subject yourself to their tactics by going to such places? Indeed, why should you be the one “in want of heart” and wander into the roadways of a “foreigner”?

The “woman stranger” that the king saw enticed the young man with an invitation to “enjoy each other with love expressions.” Have not many youths—especially girls—been exploited in a similar way? But consider: When someone tries to draw you into sexual misconduct, is it true love or selfish lust? Why would a man who genuinely loves a woman pressure her into violating her Christian training and conscience? “May your heart not turn aside” to such ways, admonishes Solomon.

The words of a seducer are usually smooth and well-calculated. Keeping wisdom and understanding at our side will help us to see through them. Never forgetting what Jehovah has commanded will safeguard us. Therefore, may we always strive to ‘keep God’s commandments and continue living,’ even forever.—[1 John 2:17].

^ (Prov. 7:10-12) Then I saw a woman meet him, Dressed like* a prostitute, with a cunning heart. 11 She is loud and defiant. She never stays* at home. 12 One moment she is outside, next she is in the public squares, She lurks near every corner.

Or “with the garment of.”

Lit., “Her feet never stay.”

^ (Gen. 38:14, 15) With that she removed her widow’s clothing and veiled herself and covered herself with a shawl and sat down at the entrance of E·naʹim, which is on the road to Timʹnah, for she saw that Sheʹlah had grown up and yet she had not been given to him as a wife. 15 When Judah caught sight of her, he at once took her for a prostitute, because she had covered her face.

^ (Prov. 7:13-15) She grabs hold of him and gives him a kiss; With a bold face, she says to him: 14 “I had to offer communion sacrifices. Today I paid my vows. 15 That is why I came out to meet you, To look for you, and I found you!

^ (Lev. 19:5, 6) “‘Now if you offer a communion sacrifice to Jehovah, you should sacrifice it in such a way that you gain approval for yourselves. 6 It should be eaten on the day of your sacrifice and on the next day, but what is left over until the third day should be burned in the fire.

^ (Lev. 22:21) “‘If a man presents a communion sacrifice to Jehovah to pay a vow or as a voluntary offering, it should be a sound animal from the herd or the flock, in order to gain approval. No defect at all should be in it.

^ (Num. 15:8-10) “‘But if you should offer a male of the herd as a burnt offering or a sacrifice to perform a special vow or communion sacrifices to Jehovah, 9 you should also present together with the male of the herd a grain offering of three tenths of an eʹphah measure of fine flour mixed with half a hin of oil. 10 You should also present wine as a drink offering, half a hin, as an offering made by fire, as a pleasing* aroma to Jehovah.

Or “appeasing; soothing.” Lit., “restful.”

^ (Prov. 7:16, 17) I have spread fine covers upon my bed, Colorful linen from Egypt. 17 I have sprinkled my bed with myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon.

^ (Prov. 7:18-20) Come, let us drink our fill of love until the morning; Let us enjoy passionate love together, 19 For my husband is not at home; He has gone on a distant journey. 20 He took a bag of money with him, And he will not return until the day of the full moon.”

^ (Prov. 7:21) She misleads him with great persuasiveness. She seduces him with smooth speech.

^ (Gen. 39:9) There is no one greater in this house than I am, and he has not withheld from me anything at all except you, because you are his wife. So how could I commit this great badness and actually sin against God?”

^ (Gen. 39:12) Then she grabbed hold of him by his garment and said: “Lie down with me!” But he left his garment in her hand and fled outside.

^ (Prov. 7:22, 23) Suddenly he goes after her, like a bull to the slaughter, Like a fool to be punished in the stocks,* 23 Until an arrow pierces his liver; Like a bird rushing into a trap, he does not know that it will cost him his life.*

Or “fetters.”

Or “soul.”

^ (Prov. 7:24-27) And now, my sons, listen to me; Pay attention to the words I speak. 25 Do not let your heart turn aside to her ways. Do not stray onto her paths, 26 For she has caused many to fall down slain, And those she has killed are numerous. 27 Her house leads to the Grave;* It goes down to the inner chambers of death.

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

^ (Prov. 7:2) Keep my commandments and live; Guard my instruction* like the pupil of your eye.

Or “law.”

^ (1 John 2:17) Furthermore, the world is passing away and so is its desire, but the one who does the will of God remains forever.

^ par. 24 Some sexually transmitted diseases damage the liver. In advanced cases of syphilis, for example, bacterial organisms overwhelm the liver. And the organism responsible for gonorrhea can cause inflammation of the liver.

^ ***w00 11/15 p. 29 “Keep My Commandments and Continue Living”***

a need to treat such instructions “like the pupil of your eyes”—guarding them with utmost care. That is the way to avoid the deadly effect of ignoring Jehovah’s standards and thus to “continue living.”

“Tie them [my commandments] upon your fingers,” continues Solomon, “and write them upon the tablet of your heart.” ([Proverbs 7:3]) As fingers are prominently before our eyes and are vital in carrying out our purposes, the lessons learned from a Scriptural upbringing or the gaining of Bible knowledge are to be a constant reminder and guide in everything we do. We are to inscribe them upon the tablet of our heart, making them a part of our nature.

Not forgetting the importance of wisdom and understanding, the king exhorts: “Say to wisdom: ‘You are my sister’; and may you call understanding itself ‘Kinswoman.’” ([Proverbs 7:4]) Wisdom is the ability to put God-given knowledge to proper use. We should have affection for wisdom as for a dearly loved sister. What is understanding? It is the ability to see into a matter and get the sense of it by grasping the connections between its parts and the whole. Understanding must be as close to us as an intimate friend.

Why should we adhere to Scriptural training and cultivate closeness with wisdom and understanding? So as “to guard [ourselves] against the woman stranger, against the foreigner who has made her own sayings smooth.” ([Proverbs 7:5]) Yes, doing so will protect us from the smooth and persuasive ways of a stranger, or foreigner—an immoral person.*

The Young Man Meets ‘a Cunning Woman’

The king of Israel next describes a scene that he himself has observed: “At the window of my house, through my lattice I looked down, that I might peer upon the inexperienced ones. I was interested in discerning among the sons a young man in want of heart, passing along on the street near her corner, and in the way to her house he marches, in the twilight, in the evening of the day, at the approach of the night and the gloom.”—Proverbs 7:6-9.

The window through which Solomon looks out has a lattice—apparently a framework with laths and perhaps elaborate carvings. As the twilight fades, the darkness of the night pours into the streets. He catches sight of a young man who is particularly vulnerable. Lacking discernment, or good sense, he is in want of heart. Likely, he is aware of the type of neighborhood he has entered and

^ (Prov. 7:3) Tie them around your fingers; Write them on the tablet of your heart.

^ (Prov. 7:4) Say to wisdom, “You are my sister,” And call understanding “my relative,”

^ (Prov. 7:5) To guard you against the wayward* woman, Against the immoral* woman and her smooth* words.

Lit., “strange.” See Pr 2:16.

Lit., “foreign.” See Pr 2:16.

Or “seductive.”

^ (Prov. 7:6-9) From the window of my house, Through my lattice, I looked down,  7 And as I observed the naive* ones, I discerned among the youths a young man lacking good sense.*  8 He passed along the street near her corner, And he marched in the direction of her house  9 In the twilight, in the evening, At the approach of night and darkness.

Or “inexperienced.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

^ par. 11 The word “stranger” was applied to those who alienated themselves from Jehovah by turning away from the Law. Thus, an immoral female, such as a prostitute, is referred to as a “woman stranger.”

^ ***w00 11/15 p. 31 “Keep My Commandments and Continue Living”***

this enticing. (Genesis 39:9,[12]) Does this young man measure up?

‘Like a Bull to the Slaughter’

“All of a sudden he is going after her,” reports Solomon, “like a bull that comes even to the slaughter, and just as if fettered for the discipline of a foolish man, until an arrow cleaves open his liver, just as a bird hastens into the trap, and he has not known that it involves his very soul.”—Proverbs 7:22, 23.

The invitation proves to be irresistible to the young man. Throwing all good sense to the wind, he goes after her ‘like a bull to the slaughter.’ As a man in fetters cannot escape his punishment, so the young man is drawn into sin. He does not see the danger of it all until “an arrow cleaves open his liver,” that is, until he receives a wound that can cause his death. The death may be physical in that he exposes himself to death-dealing sexually transmitted diseases.* The wound can also cause his spiritual death; “it involves his very soul.” His entire being and his life are seriously affected, and he has gravely sinned against God. He thus hastens into the grip of death like a bird into a trap!

“Do Not Wander Into Her Roadways”

Drawing a lesson from what he has seen, the wise king urges: “And now, O sons, listen to me and pay attention to the sayings of my mouth. May your heart not turn aside to her ways. Do not wander into her roadways. For many are the ones she has caused to fall down slain, and all those being killed by her are numerous. The ways to Sheol her house is; they are descending to the interior rooms of death.”—Proverbs 7:24-27.

Clearly, the counsel of Solomon is to turn aside from the death-dealing ways of an immoral person and “continue living.” ([Proverbs 7:2]) How timely this advice is for our day! Surely there is a need to avoid places frequented by those who are lying in wait to pick up prey. Why should you subject yourself to their tactics by going to such places? Indeed, why should you be the one “in want of heart” and wander into the roadways of a “foreigner”?

The “woman stranger” that the king saw enticed the young man with an invitation to “enjoy each other with love expressions.” Have not many youths—especially girls—been exploited in a similar way? But consider: When someone tries to draw you into sexual misconduct, is it true love or selfish lust? Why would a man who genuinely loves a woman pressure her into violating her Christian training and conscience? “May your heart not turn aside” to such ways, admonishes Solomon.

The words of a seducer are usually smooth and well-calculated. Keeping wisdom and understanding at our side will help us to see through them. Never forgetting what Jehovah has commanded will safeguard us. Therefore, may we always strive to ‘keep God’s commandments and continue living,’ even forever.—[1 John 2:17].

^ (Gen. 39:9) There is no one greater in this house than I am, and he has not withheld from me anything at all except you, because you are his wife. So how could I commit this great badness and actually sin against God?”

^ (Gen. 39:12) Then she grabbed hold of him by his garment and said: “Lie down with me!” But he left his garment in her hand and fled outside.

^ (Prov. 7:22, 23) Suddenly he goes after her, like a bull to the slaughter, Like a fool to be punished in the stocks,* 23 Until an arrow pierces his liver; Like a bird rushing into a trap, he does not know that it will cost him his life.*

Or “fetters.”

Or “soul.”

^ (Prov. 7:24-27) And now, my sons, listen to me; Pay attention to the words I speak. 25 Do not let your heart turn aside to her ways. Do not stray onto her paths, 26 For she has caused many to fall down slain, And those she has killed are numerous. 27 Her house leads to the Grave;* It goes down to the inner chambers of death.

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

^ (Prov. 7:2) Keep my commandments and live; Guard my instruction* like the pupil of your eye.

Or “law.”

^ (1 John 2:17) Furthermore, the world is passing away and so is its desire, but the one who does the will of God remains forever.

^ par. 24 Some sexually transmitted diseases damage the liver. In advanced cases of syphilis, for example, bacterial organisms overwhelm the liver. And the organism responsible for gonorrhea can cause inflammation of the liver.

^ ***w01 5/15 pp. 29-30 ‘By Wisdom Our Days Will Become Many’***

—those “in want of heart,” or those lacking understanding, as well as those lacking experience. ([Proverbs 9:4]) And a promise of life is held out to them. Wisdom contained in God’s Word, including that in the book of Proverbs, is certainly available to nearly everyone. Today, as the messengers of true wisdom, Jehovah’s Witnesses are busy inviting people, wherever they are found, to study the Bible. Taking in this knowledge, indeed, can lead to everlasting life.—[John 17:3].

Christians must humbly accept wisdom’s discipline. This is particularly true of young ones and those who have recently started to learn about Jehovah. Because of limited experience in God’s ways, they may be “in want of heart.” It is not that all of their motives are bad, but it takes time and effort to bring the heart into a condition that really pleases Jehovah God. This calls for bringing thoughts, desires, affections, and goals into harmony with what God approves. How vital that they “form a longing for the unadulterated milk belonging to the word.”—[1 Peter 2:2].

In fact, should not all of us go beyond “the primary doctrine”? Surely we need to develop an interest in “the deep things of God” and draw nourishment from the solid food that belongs to mature people. (Hebrews 5:12–6:1; 1 Corinthians 2:10) “The faithful and discreet slave,” whom Jesus Christ directly supervises, diligently provides timely spiritual food for all. (Matthew 24:45-47) May we feast at wisdom’s table by diligently studying God’s Word and the Bible-based publications provided by the slave class.

“Do Not Reprove a Ridiculer”

The teachings of wisdom also include correction and reproof. This feature of wisdom is not welcomed by all. Hence, the closing of the first section of the book of Proverbs contains a warning: “He that is correcting the ridiculer is taking to himself dishonor, and he that is giving a reproof to someone wicked—a defect in him. Do not reprove a ridiculer, that he may not hate you.”—Proverbs 9:7, 8a.

A ridiculer builds up resentment and hatred for the one trying to help make his path straight. A wicked person lacks appreciation for the value of reproof. How unwise to try to teach the beautiful truth of God’s Word to someone who hates the truth or is simply seeking to ridicule it! When the apostle Paul was preaching in Antioch, he encountered a group of Jews who had no love for the truth. They tried to embroil him in an argument by blasphemously contradicting him, but Paul simply stated: “Since you are thrusting [the word of God] away from you and do not judge yourselves worthy of everlasting life, look! we turn to the nations.”—Acts 13:45, 46.

In our endeavor to reach honesthearted ones with the Kingdom good news, may we be careful not to get involved in debates and arguments with ridiculers. Christ Jesus instructed his disciples: “When you are entering into the house, greet the household; and if the house is deserving, let the peace you wish it come upon it; but if it is not deserving, let the peace from you return upon you. Wherever anyone does not take you in or listen to your words, on going out of that house or that city shake the dust off your feet.”—Matthew 10:12-14.

A wise person’s response to reproof is opposite to that of a ridiculer. Solomon states: “Give a reproof to a wise person and he will love you. Give to a wise person and he will become still wiser.” (Proverbs 9:8b, 9a) A wise person knows that “no discipline seems for the present to be joyous, but grievous; yet afterward to those who have been trained by it it yields peaceable fruit, namely, righteousness.” (Hebrews 12:11) Although the counsel may seem painful, why should we retaliate or be defensive if accepting it is going to make us wiser?

“Impart knowledge to someone righteous and he will increase in learning,” continues the wise king. (Proverbs 9:9b) No one is too wise or too old to keep learning. What a delight it is to see even those in their twilight years accept the truth and make a dedication to Jehovah! May we also endeavor to retain the will to learn and keep the mind active.

“To You Years of Life Will Be Added”

Underscoring the main point of the subject under consideration, Solomon includes the essential prerequisite for wisdom. He writes: “The fear of Jehovah is the start of wisdom, and the knowledge of the Most Holy One is what understanding is.” (Proverbs 9:10) There can be no godly wisdom without profound, reverential awe for the true God. A person may have a mind well stocked with knowledge, but if he lacks the fear of Jehovah, he will fail to use that knowledge in a way that honors the Creator. He may even draw wrong conclusions from known facts, making himself look foolish. Moreover, the knowledge of Jehovah, the Most Holy One, is essential for gaining understanding, a notable characteristic of wisdom.

What fruitage does wisdom bear? (Proverbs 8:12-21,[35]) The king of Israel says: “By me your days will become many, and to you years of life will be added.” (Proverbs 9:11) Length of days and years of life are the result of keeping company with wisdom. Yes, “wisdom itself preserves alive its owners.”—Ecclesiastes 7:12.

Putting forth effort to gain wisdom is our personal responsibility. Emphasizing this fact, Solomon states: “If you have become wise, you have become wise in your own behalf; and if you have ridiculed, you will bear it, just you alone.” (Proverbs 9:12) The wise one is wise to his own benefit, and the ridiculer alone is to blame for his own suffering. Indeed, we reap what we sow. May we, then, “pay attention to wisdom.”—[Proverbs 2:2].

“A Woman of Stupidity Is Boisterous”

By way of contrast, Solomon next says: “A woman of stupidity is boisterous. She is simplemindedness itself and has come to know nothing whatever. And she has seated herself at the entrance of her house, upon a seat, in the high places of the town, to call out to those passing along the way, those who are going straight ahead on their paths: ‘Whoever is inexperienced, let him turn aside here.’”—Proverbs 9:13-16a.

Stupidity is portrayed as a loud, undisciplined, and ignorant woman. She too has built a house. And she has taken upon herself the task of calling out to whoever is inexperienced. So the passersby have a choice. Will they accept wisdom’s invitation or that of stupidity?

“Stolen Waters Themselves Are Sweet”

Both wisdom and stupidity invite listeners to “turn aside here.” The appeal, however, is different. Wisdom invites people to a feast of wine, meat, and bread. The attraction that stupidity holds out reminds us of the ways of a loose woman. Solomon says: “Whoever is in want of heart—she has also said to him: ‘Stolen waters themselves are sweet, and bread eaten in secrecy—it is pleasant.’”—Proverbs 9:16b, 17.

^ (Prov. 9:4) “Whoever is inexperienced, let him come in here.” She says to the one lacking good sense:*

Lit., “in want of heart.”

^ (John 17:3) This means everlasting life, their coming to know you,* the only true God, and the one whom you sent, Jesus Christ.

Or “their taking in knowledge of you.”

^ (1 Pet. 2:2) As newborn infants, form a longing for the unadulterated* milk of the word, so that by means of it you may grow to salvation,

Or “pure.”

^ (Heb. 5:12-6:1) For although by now* you should be teachers, you again need someone to teach you from the beginning the elementary things of the sacred pronouncements of God, and you have gone back to needing milk, not solid food. 13 For everyone who continues to feed on milk is unacquainted with the word of righteousness, for he is a young child. 14 But solid food belongs to mature people, to those who through use have their powers of discernment* trained to distinguish both right and wrong.

6 Therefore, now that we have moved beyond the primary doctrine about the Christ, let us press on to maturity, not laying a foundation again, namely, repentance from dead works and faith in God,

Lit., “in view of the time.”

Or “their perceptive powers.”

^ (1 Cor. 2:10) For it is to us God has revealed them through his spirit, for the spirit searches into all things, even the deep things of God.

^ (Matt. 24:45-47) “Who really is the faithful and discreet* slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time? 46 Happy is that slave if his master on coming finds him doing so! 47 Truly I say to you, he will appoint him over all his belongings.

Or “wise.”

^ (Prov. 9:7, 8) The one who corrects a ridiculer invites dishonor, And whoever reproves someone wicked will get hurt.  8 Do not reprove a ridiculer, or he will hate you. Reprove a wise person, and he will love you.

^ (Acts 13:45, 46) When the Jews saw the crowds, they were filled with jealousy and began blasphemously contradicting the things Paul was saying. 46 Then Paul and Barʹna·bas boldly said to them: “It was necessary for the word of God to be spoken first to you. Since you are rejecting it and do not judge yourselves worthy of everlasting life, look! we turn to the nations.

^ (Matt. 10:12-14) When you enter the house, greet the household. 13 If the house is deserving, let the peace you wish it come upon it; but if it is not deserving, let the peace from you return upon you. 14 Wherever anyone does not receive you or listen to your words, on going out of that house or that city, shake the dust off your feet.

^ (Prov. 9:8, 9) Do not reprove a ridiculer, or he will hate you. Reprove a wise person, and he will love you.  9 Share with a wise person, and he will become wiser. Teach someone righteous, and he will add to his learning.

^ (Heb. 12:11) True, no discipline seems for the present to be joyous, but it is painful;* yet afterward, it yields the peaceable fruit of righteousness to those who have been trained by it.

Or “grievous.”

^ (Prov. 9:9) Share with a wise person, and he will become wiser. Teach someone righteous, and he will add to his learning.

^ (Prov. 9:10) The fear of Jehovah is the beginning of wisdom, And knowledge of the Most Holy One is understanding.

^ (Prov. 8:12-21) I, wisdom, dwell together with shrewdness; I have found knowledge and thinking ability. 13 The fear of Jehovah means the hating of bad. I hate self-exaltation and pride and the evil way and perverse speech. 14 I possess good advice and practical wisdom; Understanding and power are mine. 15 By me kings keep reigning, And high officials decree righteousness. 16 By me princes keep ruling, And nobles judge in righteousness. 17 I love those loving me, And those seeking me will find me. 18 Riches and glory are with me, Lasting wealth* and righteousness. 19 My fruitage is better than gold, even refined gold, And what I produce is better than the finest silver. 20 I walk in the path of righteousness, In the middle of the pathways of justice; 21 I give a rich inheritance to those who love me, And I fill up their storehouses.

Or “Hereditary values.”

^ (Prov. 8:35) For the one finding me will find life, And he receives approval from Jehovah.

^ (Prov. 9:11) For by me your days will be many, And years will be added to your life.

^ (Eccl. 7:12) For wisdom is a protection just as money is a protection, but the advantage of knowledge is this: Wisdom preserves the life of its owner.

^ (Prov. 9:12) If you become wise, you are wise to your own advantage, But if you are a ridiculer, you alone will bear it.

^ (Prov. 2:2) By making your ear attentive to wisdom And inclining your heart to discernment;

^ (Prov. 9:13-16) A stupid woman is loud. She is ignorant and knows absolutely nothing. 14 She sits at the entrance of her house On a seat in the high places of the city, 15 Calling out to those passing by, To those walking straight ahead on their way: 16 “Whoever is inexperienced, let him come in here.” She says to those lacking good sense:*

Lit., “in want of heart.”

^ (Prov. 9:16, 17) “Whoever is inexperienced, let him come in here.” She says to those lacking good sense:* 17 “Stolen waters are sweet, And food eaten in secret is pleasant.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

^ ***w06 5/15 pp. 26-30 The Joys of Walking in Integrity***

3. On what will we focus our attention in this article?

3 “The blessing of Jehovah—that is what makes rich, and he adds no pain with it,” states Proverbs 10:22. Is not the spiritually prosperous condition of the modern-day servants of Jehovah a blessing to rejoice over? Let us consider some aspects of our spiritual prosperity and see what they mean to us personally. Taking time to reflect on the favors that Jehovah has showered upon ‘the righteous one walking in his integrity’ will indeed strengthen our resolve to continue serving our heavenly Father joyfully.—Proverbs 20:7.

‘Blessings That Make Us Rich’ Now

4, 5. Which Bible teaching do you especially appreciate, and why?

4 An accurate knowledge of Bible teachings. The religions of Christendom generally claim to believe the Bible. However, they fail to agree on what it teaches. Even members of the same religious group often differ in their views of what the Scriptures really teach. How different their condition is from that of Jehovah’s servants! Regardless of our national, cultural, or ethnic background, we worship the God we know by name. He is not some mysterious triune god. (Deuteronomy 6:4; Psalm 83:18;[Mark 12:29]) We are also aware that the paramount issue of God’s universal sovereignty is due for settlement and that by maintaining our integrity to him, each one of us is personally involved in that issue. We know the truth about the dead and are free of the morbid fear of a God who is said to torment humans in hellfire or consign them to purgatory.—Ecclesiastes 9:5,[10].

5 Moreover, what a joy it is to know that we are not an accidental product of blind evolution! Rather, we are God’s creation, made in his own image. (Genesis 1:26; Malachi 2:10) “I shall laud you because in a fear-inspiring way I am wonderfully made,” sang the psalmist to his God. “Your works are wonderful, as my soul is very well aware.”—[Psalm 139:14].

6, 7. What changes in your life or in the life of others you know have proved to be a blessing?

6 Release from detrimental habits and practices. Warnings about the dangers of smoking, excessive drinking, and sexual promiscuity abound in the media. For the most part, these warnings go unheeded. What happens, though, when a sincere person learns that the true God condemns such things and is saddened by those who practice them? Why, that person is moved to exclude such practices from his life! (Isaiah 63:10; 1 Corinthians 6:9, 10; 2 Corinthians 7:1; Ephesians 4:30) While he does this primarily to please Jehovah God, he also receives additional benefits—better health and peace of mind.

7 Breaking bad habits is very difficult for many. Still, each year tens of thousands are doing so. They dedicate themselves to Jehovah and submit to water baptism, thus making it public that they have eliminated from their lives the practices that displease God. What an encouragement that is to all of us! Our determination to remain free from enslavement to sinful and hurtful conduct is reinforced.

8. What Bible-based counsel contributes to family happiness?

8 Happy family life. In numerous countries family life is faltering. Many marriages end in divorce, often leaving behind painfully scarred children. In some European countries, one-parent families make up close to 20 percent of all households. How has Jehovah helped us walk in the way of integrity in this regard? Please read Ephesians 5:22–6:4, and note the fine counsel that God’s Word gives to husbands, wives, and children. Applying what is stated there and elsewhere in the Scriptures certainly strengthens the marriage bond, helps parents to bring up children properly, and contributes to a happy family life. Is that not a blessing to rejoice over?

9, 10. How does our outlook for the future differ from that of the world?

9 Assurance that world problems will soon be solved. Despite scientific and technological know-how and the sincere efforts of certain leaders, serious problems of present-day life remain unsolved. Klaus Schwab, founder of the World Economic Forum, recently noted that “the list of challenges facing the world grows ever longer and the time to address them grows shorter.” He spoke of “dangers that transcend national boundaries like terrorism, environmental degradation and financial instability.” Schwab concluded: “Now, more than ever, the world is faced with realities that call for collective and decisive action.” As the 21st century moves forward, the overall outlook for mankind’s future remains bleak.

10 How gratifying to know that Jehovah has instituted an arrangement that is capable of solving all of mankind’s problems—the Messianic Kingdom of God! By means of it, the true God will ‘make wars to cease’ and bring about ‘abundant peace.’ ([Psalm 46:9;][72:7]) The anointed King, Jesus Christ, ‘will deliver the poor one, the afflicted one, and the lowly one from oppression and from violence.’ (Psalm 72:12-14) Under Kingdom rule, there will be no food shortage. ([Psalm 72:16]) Jehovah “will wipe out every tear from [our] eyes, and death will be no more, neither will mourning nor outcry nor pain be anymore. The former things have passed away.” (Revelation 21:4) The Kingdom has already been established in heaven and will shortly take the necessary action to affect every affair on the earth.—[Daniel 2:44;] Revelation 11:15.

11, 12. (a) Does pursuit of pleasure bring lasting happiness? Explain. (b) What brings true happiness?

11 Knowing what brings true happiness. What does bring true happiness? One psychologist said that happiness has three components—pleasure, engagement (involvement in such activities as work and family), and meaning (working toward a larger end or goal than self). Of the three, he listed pleasure as the least consequential and observed: “This is newsworthy because so many people build their lives around pursuing pleasure.” What is the Bible’s view in this regard?

12 King Solomon of ancient Israel stated: “I said, even I, in my heart: ‘Do come now, let me try you out with rejoicing. Also, see good.’ And, look! that too was vanity. I said to laughter: ‘Insanity!’ and to rejoicing: ‘What is this doing?’” (Ecclesiastes 2:1, 2) Scripturally, whatever happiness pleasure offers is at best temporary. What about involvement in work? We have the most meaningful work to get involved in—the Kingdom-preaching and disciple-making work. (Matthew 24:14;[28:19, 20]) By sharing with others the message of salvation outlined in the Bible, we engage in a work that can result in our own salvation and in that of those who listen to us. (1 Timothy 4:16) As “God’s fellow workers,” we experience that “there is more happiness in giving than there is in receiving.” (1 Corinthians 3:9;[Acts 20:35]) This work adds meaning to our life and provides the Creator with an answer for his taunter, Satan the Devil. (Proverbs 27:11) Indeed, Jehovah has shown us that godly devotion brings genuine and lasting happiness.—1 Timothy 4:8.

13. (a) In what way is the Theocratic Ministry School a blessing for us to rejoice over? (b) How have you benefited from the Theocratic Ministry School?

13 An important and effective training program. Gerhard serves as an elder in a congregation of Jehovah’s Witnesses. Recalling his youth, he says: “As a young person, I had great problems speaking. When under pressure, I could scarcely articulate and would begin to stutter. I felt inferior and developed a complex. My parents arranged for me to take a speaking course, but their efforts were to no avail. My problem was psychological, not physical. There was, though, a wonderful provision from Jehovah—the Theocratic Ministry School. Enrolling in this school gave me renewed courage. I tried my best to practice what I learned. And it worked! I became freer, lost my complex, and became more courageous in the ministry. Now I even deliver public talks. I am truly grateful to Jehovah, who gave me a new life through this school.” Is not the way Jehovah trains us to do his work a reason to be joyful?

14, 15. In times of distress, what help is readily available? Illustrate.

14 A personal relationship with Jehovah and support from the united international brotherhood. Katrin, who lives in Germany, was greatly dismayed upon hearing reports of a severe earthquake and resultant tsunami in southeast Asia. Her daughter was visiting Thailand when the catastrophe hit. For 32 hours this mother did not know whether her daughter was alive or was among the casualties that mounted hour by hour. How relieved Katrin was finally to receive a telephone call that assured her of her daughter’s safety!

15 What helped Katrin during those hours of anxiety? She writes: “I spent almost all of this time in prayer to Jehovah. I noticed over and over again how much strength and peace of mind this gave me. Moreover, loving spiritual brothers visited me and stood by my side.” (Philippians 4:6, 7) How much worse her situation would have been if she had had to spend those agonizing hours without the benefit of prayer to Jehovah and the comfort of a loving spiritual brotherhood! Our intimate relationship with Jehovah and his Son along with our close association with the Christian brotherhood is a unique blessing, too precious to be taken for granted.

16. Give an experience that illustrates the value of the resurrection hope.

16 The hope of seeing dead loved ones again. (John 5:28, 29) A young man named Matthias was raised as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses. Unaware of his blessings, however, he drifted away from the Christian congregation when he was a teenager. He now writes: “I never really had deep discussions with my father. Over the years, we had many arguments. Still, my father always wanted the best for me. He loved me dearly, something I failed to realize at the time. In 1996, as I sat at his bedside, holding his hand and crying bitterly, I told him how sorry I was for all that I had done and that I loved him so much. But he could not hear me. After a short illness, he slipped away in death. If I live to see my father in the resurrection, we will make up for the past. And he will surely be happy to hear that I now serve as an elder and that my wife and I are privileged to serve as pioneers.” What a blessing the resurrection hope is to us!

^ par. 3 (Prov. 10:22) It is the blessing of Jehovah that makes one rich, And He adds no pain* with it.

Or “sorrow; hardship.”

^ par. 3 (Prov. 20:7) The righteous one is walking in his integrity. Happy are his children* who come after him.

Lit., “sons.”

^ par. 4 (Deut. 6:4) “Listen, O Israel: Jehovah our God is one Jehovah.

^ par. 4 (Ps. 83:18) May people know that you, whose name is Jehovah, You alone are the Most High over all the earth.

^ par. 4 (Mark 12:29) Jesus answered: “The first is, ‘Hear, O Israel, Jehovah* our God is one Jehovah,*

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

^ par. 4 (Eccl. 9:5) For the living know* that they will die, but the dead know nothing at all, nor do they have any more reward,* because all memory of them is forgotten.

Or “are conscious.”

Or “wages.”

^ par. 4 (Eccl. 9:10) Whatever your hand finds to do, do with all your might, for there is no work nor planning nor knowledge nor wisdom in the Grave,* where you are going.

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

^ par. 5 (Gen. 1:26) Then God said: “Let us make man in our image, according to our likeness, and let them have in subjection the fish of the sea and the flying creatures of the heavens and the domestic animals and all the earth and every creeping animal that is moving on the earth.”

^ par. 5 (Mal. 2:10) “Do we not all have one father? Was it not one God who created us? So why do we deal treacherously with one another, profaning the covenant of our forefathers?

^ par. 5 (Ps. 139:14) I praise you because in an awe-inspiring way I am wonderfully made. Your works are wonderful, I know* this very well.

Or “My soul knows.”

^ par. 6 (Isa. 63:10) But they rebelled and grieved his holy spirit. He then turned into their enemy, And he fought against them.

^ par. 6 (1 Cor. 6:9, 10) Or do you not know that unrighteous people will not inherit God’s Kingdom? Do not be misled.* Those who are sexually immoral,* idolaters, adulterers, men who submit to homosexual acts, men who practice homosexuality,* 10 thieves, greedy people, drunkards, revilers,* and extortioners will not inherit God’s Kingdom.

Or “deceived.”

See Glossary, “Sexual immorality.”

Or “men who have sex with men.” Lit., “men who lie with men.”

Or “the verbally abusive.”

^ par. 6 (2 Cor. 7:1) Therefore, since we have these promises, beloved ones, let us cleanse ourselves of every defilement of flesh and spirit, perfecting holiness in the fear of God.

^ par. 6 (Eph. 4:30) Also, do not be grieving* God’s holy spirit, with which you have been sealed for a day of releasing by ransom.

Or “cause sorrow to.”

^ par. 8 (Eph. 5:22-6:4) Let wives be in subjection to their husbands as to the Lord, 23 because a husband is head of his wife just as the Christ is head of the congregation, he being a savior of this body. 24 In fact, as the congregation is in subjection to the Christ, wives should also be to their husbands in everything. 25 Husbands, continue loving your wives, just as the Christ also loved the congregation and gave himself up for it, 26 in order that he might sanctify it, cleansing it with the bath of water by means of the word, 27 so that he might present the congregation to himself in its splendor, without a spot or a wrinkle or any of such things, but holy and without blemish. 28 In the same way husbands should love their wives as their own bodies. A man who loves his wife loves himself, 29 for no man ever hated his own body,* but he feeds and cherishes it, just as the Christ does the congregation, 30 because we are members of his body. 31 “For this reason a man will leave his father and his mother and he will stick to* his wife, and the two will be one flesh.” 32 This sacred secret is great. Now I am speaking about Christ and the congregation. 33 Nevertheless, each one of you must love his wife as he does himself; on the other hand, the wife should have deep respect for her husband.

6 Children, be obedient to your parents in union with the Lord, for this is righteous. 2 “Honor your father and your mother” is the first command with a promise: 3 “That it may go well with you* and you may remain a long time on the earth.” 4 And fathers, do not be irritating your children, but go on bringing them up in the discipline and admonition* of Jehovah.*

Lit., “flesh.”

Or “remain with.”

Or “That you may prosper.”

Or “instruction; guidance.” Lit., “putting mind in.”

See App. A5.

^ par. 10 (Ps. 46:9) He is bringing an end to wars throughout the earth. He breaks the bow and shatters the spear; He burns the military wagons* with fire.

Or possibly, “the shields.”

^ par. 10 (Ps. 72:7) In his days the righteous will flourish,* And peace will abound until the moon is no more.

Lit., “sprout.”

^ par. 10 (Ps. 72:12-14) For he will rescue the poor who cry for help, Also the lowly one and whoever has no helper. 13 He will have pity on the lowly and the poor, And the lives* of the poor he will save. 14 From oppression and from violence he will rescue them,* And their blood will be precious in his eyes.

Or “souls.”

Or “redeem their souls.”

^ par. 10 (Ps. 72:16) There will be an abundance of grain on the earth; On the top of the mountains it will overflow. His fruit will flourish as in Lebʹa·non, And in the cities people will blossom like the vegetation of the earth.

^ par. 10 (Rev. 21:4) And he will wipe out every tear from their eyes, and death will be no more, neither will mourning nor outcry nor pain be anymore. The former things have passed away.”

^ par. 10 (Dan. 2:44) “In the days of those kings the God of heaven will set up a kingdom that will never be destroyed. And this kingdom will not be passed on to any other people. It will crush and put an end to all these kingdoms, and it alone will stand forever,

^ par. 10 (Rev. 11:15) The seventh angel blew his trumpet. And there were loud voices in heaven, saying: “The kingdom of the world has become the Kingdom of our Lord and of his Christ, and he will rule as king forever and ever.”

^ par. 12 (Eccl. 2:1, 2) Then I said in my heart: “Come and let me try out pleasure* and see what good comes.” But look! that too was futility.  2 I said about laughter, “It is madness!” And about pleasure,* “What use is it?”

Or “rejoicing.”

Or “rejoicing.”

^ par. 12 (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ par. 12 (Matt. 28:19, 20) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”*

Or “the age.” See Glossary.

^ par. 12 (1 Tim. 4:16) Pay constant attention to yourself and to your teaching. Persevere in these things, for by doing this you will save both yourself and those who listen to you.

^ par. 12 (1 Cor. 3:9) For we are God’s fellow workers. You are God’s field under cultivation, God’s building.

^ par. 12 (Acts 20:35) I have shown you in all things that by working hard in this way, you must assist those who are weak and must keep in mind the words of the Lord Jesus, when he himself said: ‘There is more happiness in giving than there is in receiving.’”

^ par. 12 (Prov. 27:11) Be wise, my son, and make my heart rejoice, So that I can make a reply to him who taunts me.

^ par. 12 (1 Tim. 4:8) For physical training* is beneficial for a little, but godly devotion is beneficial for all things, as it holds promise of the life now and the life that is to come.

Or “exercise.”

^ par. 15 (Phil. 4:6, 7) Do not be anxious over anything, but in everything by prayer and supplication along with thanksgiving, let your petitions be made known to God; 7 and the peace of God that surpasses all understanding will guard your hearts and your mental powers* by means of Christ Jesus.

Or “your minds; your thoughts.”

^ par. 16 (John 5:28, 29) Do not be amazed at this, for the hour is coming in which all those in the memorial tombs will hear his voice 29 and come out, those who did good things to a resurrection of life, and those who practiced vile things to a resurrection of judgment.

^ ***bh p. 176 Baptism and Your Relationship With God***

KNOWLEDGE AND FAITH NEEDED

5. (a) What is the first step in qualifying for baptism? (b) Why are Christian meetings important?

5 You have already begun to take the first step. How? By coming to know Jehovah God and Jesus Christ, perhaps by means of a systematic study of the Bible. (Read John 17:3.) But there is more to learn. Christians want to be “filled with the accurate knowledge of [God’s] will.” (Colossians 1:9) Attending the congregation meetings of Jehovah’s Witnesses is a big help in this regard. It is important to attend such meetings. (Hebrews 10:24, 25) Regular meeting attendance will help you come to know God.

6. How much Bible knowledge must you have in order to qualify for baptism?

6 Of course, you do not need to know everything in the Bible in order to qualify for baptism. The Ethiopian court official had some knowledge, but he needed help to understand certain parts of the Scriptures. (Acts 8:30, 31) Likewise, you still have much to learn. In fact, you will never stop learning about God. (Ecclesiastes 3:11) Before you can get baptized, however, you need to know and accept at least the basic Bible teachings. ([Hebrews 5:12]) Such teachings include the truth about the condition of the dead and the importance of God’s name and his Kingdom.

^ par. 5 (John 17:3) This means everlasting life, their coming to know you,* the only true God, and the one whom you sent, Jesus Christ.

Or “their taking in knowledge of you.”

^ par. 5 (Col. 1:9) That is also why from the day we heard of it, we have never stopped praying for you and asking that you may be filled with the accurate knowledge of his will in all wisdom and spiritual comprehension,

^ par. 5 (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ par. 6 (Acts 8:30, 31) Philip ran alongside and heard him reading aloud Isaiah the prophet, and he said: “Do you actually know* what you are reading?” 31 He said: “Really, how could I ever do so unless someone guided me?” So he urged Philip to get on and sit down with him.

Or “understand.”

^ par. 6 (Eccl. 3:11) He has made everything beautiful* in its time. He has even put eternity in their heart; yet mankind will never find out the work that the true God has made from start to finish.

Or “well-arranged; proper; appropriate.”

^ par. 6 (Heb. 5:12) For although by now* you should be teachers, you again need someone to teach you from the beginning the elementary things of the sacred pronouncements of God, and you have gone back to needing milk, not solid food.

Lit., “in view of the time.”

^ ***sn song 83 We Need Self-Control***

Song 83

We Need Self-Control

(Romans 7:14-25)

1. We love Jehovah with heart, mind, and soul;

But since we are sinful, we need self-control.

Minding the flesh brings trouble and strife.

Minding the spirit means peace and life.

2. Satan’s temptations confront us each day,

And sin’s law within us can lead us astray.

Power of truth is greater than sin.

Thanks to Jehovah, our minds can win.

3. Each word and action reflects on God’s name,

So we must endeavor to keep free from blame.

In all we do, we make this our goal:

Always maintaining our self-control.

(See also [1 Cor. 9:25;][Gal. 5:23;][2 Pet. 1:6].)

^ (Rom. 7:14-25) For we know that the Law is spiritual, but I am fleshly, sold under sin. 15 For I do not understand what I am doing. For I do not practice what I wish, but I do what I hate. 16 However, if I do what I do not wish, I agree that the Law is fine. 17 But now I am no longer the one doing it, but it is the sin that resides in me. 18 For I know that in me, that is, in my flesh, there dwells nothing good; for I have the desire to do what is fine but not the ability to carry it out. 19 For I do not do the good that I wish, but the bad that I do not wish is what I practice. 20 If, then, I do what I do not wish, I am no longer the one carrying it out, but it is the sin dwelling in me. 21 I find, then, this law in my case: When I wish to do what is right, what is bad is present with me. 22 I really delight in the law of God according to the man I am within, 23 but I see in my body* another law warring against the law of my mind and leading me captive to sin’s law that is in my body.* 24 Miserable man that I am! Who will rescue me from the body undergoing this death? 25 Thanks to God through Jesus Christ our Lord! So, then, with my mind I myself am a slave to God’s law, but with my flesh to sin’s law.

Lit., “members.”

Lit., “members.”

^ (1 Cor. 9:25) Now everyone competing in a contest* exercises self-control in all things. Of course, they do it to receive a crown that can perish, but we, one that does not perish.

Or “every athlete.”

^ (Gal. 5:23) mildness, self-control. Against such things there is no law.

^ (2 Pet. 1:6) to your knowledge self-control, to your self-control endurance, to your endurance godly devotion,

^ ***kr pp. 16-19 The Kingdom Is Born in Heaven***

13, 14. (a) How did the “messenger” help to prepare the way for the Messianic King? (b) What can we learn from our brothers of more than a century ago?

13 Consider this: Would people have been prepared for the beginning of Christ’s presence if they were not able to distinguish Jesus from his Father, Jehovah? Surely not! Nor would they have been prepared if they thought that immortality was the automatic possession of all and not a precious gift bestowed on only relatively few of Christ’s footstep followers; nor if they thought that God tormented people in hellfire for all eternity with no hope of relief! Without doubt, the “messenger” prepared the way for the Messianic King!

14 And what about us today? What can we learn from our brothers of more than a century ago? We likewise need to be avid readers and students of God’s Word. ([John 17:3]) As this materialistic world becomes emaciated, spiritually speaking, may our appetite for spiritual food grow ever stronger!—Read 1 Timothy 4:15.

“Get Out of Her, My People”

15. The Bible Students gradually came to what realization? (See also footnote.)

15 The Bible Students taught that it was necessary to break away from worldly churches. In 1879, the Watch Tower referred to the “Babylon church.” Was it talking about the papacy? The Roman Catholic Church? Protestant denominations had for centuries made such applications of Babylon as a prophetic type in Scripture. However, the Bible Students gradually came to the realization that all the churches of Christendom were included in modern-day “Babylon.” Why? Because they all taught doctrinal lies such as those discussed above.* In time, our publications became more and more direct about what honesthearted members of Babylon’s churches should do.

16, 17. (a) How did Volume III of Millennial Dawn and the Watch Tower urge people to remove themselves from false religion? (b) What factor diluted such early warnings? (See footnote.)

16 For example, in 1891, Volume III of Millennial Dawn discussed God’s rejection of modern-day Babylon and noted: “The whole system—a system of systems—is rejected.” It added that all those “not in sympathy with her false doctrines and practices are now called to separate themselves from her.”

17 In January 1900, the Watch Tower offered counsel to those who still kept their names on the denominational rolls of Christendom’s churches and who rationalized their course, saying, “My sympathies are all with the truth, and I rarely attend other meetings.” The article asked: “But is this right—to be half out and half in Babylon? Is this the obedience required . . . and pleasing and acceptable to God? Surely not. He [the church member] publicly entered into a covenant with the denomination when he joined it, and he should faithfully live up to all the conditions of that covenant until he . . . publicly renounces or cancels his membership.” Over the years, that message became stronger.* Servants of Jehovah must renounce all ties with false religion.

18. Why was it necessary for people to get out of Babylon the Great?

18 If such warnings to get out of Babylon the Great had not been sounded regularly, would Christ as the newly installed King have had a body of prepared, anointed servants on earth? Surely not, for only Christians who are free from Babylon’s grip can worship Jehovah “with spirit and truth.” ([John 4:24]) Are we today likewise determined to keep free from false religion? Let us keep obeying the command: “Get out of her, my people”!—Read Revelation 18:4.

Gathering for Worship

19, 20. How did the Watch Tower encourage God’s people to gather together for worship?

19 The Bible Students taught that fellow believers should gather together for worship, where that was possible. For genuine Christians, it is not enough to get out of false religion. It is vital to take part in pure worship as well. From its early issues, the Watch Tower encouraged readers to gather together for worship. For example, in July 1880, Brother Russell reported on a speaking tour he had made, commenting on how encouraging the many meetings had been. He then urged readers to send in cards regarding their progress—some of which would be published in the journal’s pages. To what end? “Let us all know . . . how the Lord prospers you; whether you keep up your meetings with those of like precious faith.”

20 In 1882, an article called “Assembling Together” appeared in the Watch Tower. The article exhorted Christians to hold meetings “for mutual edification, encouragement and strengthening.” It noted: “It matters not whether there is any one learned or talented among you. Let each one bring his own Bible, paper, and pencil, and avail yourselves of as many helps in the way of a Concordance, . . . as possible. Choose your subject; ask for the Spirit’s guidance in the understanding of it; then read, think, compare scripture with scripture and you will assuredly be guided into truth.”

21. The congregation in Allegheny, Pennsylvania, set what example regarding meetings and shepherding?

21 The Bible Students had their headquarters in Allegheny, Pennsylvania, U.S.A. There they set a fine example by gathering together in obedience to the inspired counsel recorded at Hebrews 10:24, 25. (Read.) Much later, an elderly brother named Charles Capen recalled attending those meetings as a boy. He wrote: “I still remember one of the scripture texts painted on the wall of the Society’s assembly hall. ‘One is your Master, even Christ; and all ye are brethren.’ That text has always stood out in my mind—there is no clergy-laity distinction among Jehovah’s people.” ([Matt. 23:8]) Brother Capen also recalled the stimulating meetings, the warm encouragement, and Brother Russell’s diligent efforts to shepherd every member of the congregation personally.

22. How did faithful people respond to the encouragement to attend Christian meetings, and what lesson may we learn from them?

22 Faithful people responded to this example and to the instruction given. Congregations formed in other states, such as Ohio and Michigan, and then all over North America and in other lands. Consider: Would faithful people have truly been prepared for the presence of Christ if they had not been trained to obey the inspired counsel to meet together for worship? Surely not! What about us today? We need to be just as determined to attend Christian meetings faithfully, seeking every opportunity to worship together and be spiritually upbuilding to one another.

^ par. 14 (John 17:3) This means everlasting life, their coming to know you,* the only true God, and the one whom you sent, Jesus Christ.

Or “their taking in knowledge of you.”

^ par. 14 (1 Tim. 4:15) Ponder over* these things; be absorbed in them, so that your advancement may be plainly seen by all people.

Or “Meditate on.”

^ par. 18 (John 4:24) God is a Spirit, and those worshipping him must worship with spirit and truth.”

^ par. 18 (Rev. 18:4) And I heard another voice out of heaven say: “Get out of her, my people, if you do not want to share with her in her sins, and if you do not want to receive part of her plagues.

^ par. 21 (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ par. 21 (Matt. 23:8) But you, do not you be called Rabbi, for one is your Teacher, and all of you are brothers.

^ par. 15 Although the Bible Students saw the need to withdraw from religious organizations that were friends of the world, for years they continued to view as Christian brothers individuals who, although not Bible Students, professed belief in the ransom and claimed to be dedicated to God.

^ par. 17 One factor that diluted the force of such early warnings was that they were applied mainly to Christ’s little flock of 144,000. We will see in Chapter 5 that prior to 1935, it was thought that the “great multitude,” as described at Revelation 7:9, 10 in the King James Version, would include countless members of the churches of Christendom and that they would be made a secondary heavenly class as a reward for siding with Christ at the very end.

^ (Rev. 7:9, 10) After this I saw, and look! a great crowd, which no man was able to number, out of all nations and tribes and peoples and tongues,* standing before the throne and before the Lamb, dressed in white robes; and there were palm branches in their hands. 10 And they keep shouting with a loud voice, saying: “Salvation we owe to our God, who is seated on the throne, and to the Lamb.”

Or “languages.”

^ ***snnw song 152 Our Strength, Our Hope, Our Confidence***

Song 152

Our Strength, Our Hope, Our Confidence

Download:

Lyrics Only

Lead Sheet

(Proverbs 14:26)

O Jehovah, you have given us

a hope that we hold dear.

It’s a hope we find so thrilling

we want the world to hear.

But at times this life’s anxieties

are the cause of fears within,

And the hope that burned so brightly

has suddenly grown dim.

(CHORUS)

You’re our strength, you’re our hope,

you’re our confidence.

Whatever we lack, you supply.

When we preach, when we teach,

we have confidence

because it’s on you we rely.

So Jehovah, please instill in us

a heart that won’t forget,

For you’ve always been our comfort

when troubled times we’ve met.

And these thoughts that lift and strengthen us

can revive that dying flame,

For they fill our hearts with courage

to speak about your name.

(CHORUS)

You’re our strength, you’re our hope,

you’re our confidence.

Whatever we lack, you supply.

When we preach, when we teach,

we have confidence

because it’s on you we rely.

(See also Ps. 72:13, 14; Prov. 3:5, 6,[26;][Jer. 17:7].)

^ (Prov. 14:26) There is strong confidence in the fear of Jehovah, And it will be a refuge for his children.

^ (Ps. 72:13, 14) He will have pity on the lowly and the poor, And the lives* of the poor he will save. 14 From oppression and from violence he will rescue them,* And their blood will be precious in his eyes.

Or “souls.”

Or “redeem their souls.”

^ (Prov. 3:5, 6) Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, And do not rely* on your own understanding.  6 In all your ways take notice of him, And he will make your paths straight.

Lit., “lean.”

^ (Prov. 3:26) For Jehovah will prove to be your source of confidence; He will keep your foot from being caught.

^ (Jer. 17:7) Blessed is the man* who puts his trust in Jehovah, Whose confidence is in Jehovah.

Or “strong man.”